<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Metallica. Or The treatise of metallica Briefly comprehending the doctrine of diuerse new metallicall inuentions, but especially, how to neale, melt, and worke all kinde of mettle-oares, irons and steeles with sea-coale, pit-coale, earth-coale and brush-fewell. Also a transcript of his Maiesties letters pattents of priuiledge, granted vnto Simon Sturteuant for the said metallicall businesses, for one and thirty yeares. Published in print before the last day of this present Easter terme, as the said Simon Sturteuant was by his Highnesse inioyned.</title>
            <author>Sturtevant, Simon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853145</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1293:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Metallica. Or The treatise of metallica Briefly comprehending the doctrine of diuerse new metallicall inuentions, but especially, how to neale, melt, and worke all kinde of mettle-oares, irons and steeles with sea-coale, pit-coale, earth-coale and brush-fewell. Also a transcript of his Maiesties letters pattents of priuiledge, granted vnto Simon Sturteuant for the said metallicall businesses, for one and thirty yeares. Published in print before the last day of this present Easter terme, as the said Simon Sturteuant was by his Highnesse inioyned.</title>
                  <author>Sturtevant, Simon.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By George Eld. Cum priuilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1612. May. 22.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter patent is dated on B3r: the xxix. day of February, in the yeares of the reigne of our soueraigne lord Iames .. the ninth, &amp; of Scotland the xlv.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Metallurgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inventions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Metallica. <hi>OR</hi> The Treatiſe of Metallica.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Briefly comprehending the Doctrine of diuerſe new</hi> Metallicall <hi>Inuentions, but eſpecially,</hi> how to neale, melt, and worke all kinde of mettle-oares, Irons and Steeles with Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale and Bruſh-fewell.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Tranſcript of his Maieſties Letters <hi>Pattents of Priuiledge, granted vnto</hi> Simon Sturteuant <hi>for the ſaid</hi> Metallicall <hi>buſineſſes,</hi> for one and thirty yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed in Print before the last day of this</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Eaſter Terme, as the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> was by his Highneſſe inioyned.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>George Eld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno. 1612. May. 22.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, how they that are willing to apprehend and aſſiſt new bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes, are deſirous to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in theſe points. Firſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the perfect and exact knowledge of that Inuention wherein they are to deale and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate, for as the common Prouerbe ſaith; <hi>Ignoti nulla cupido.</hi> The ſecond is, touching the worth and goodneſſe of the buſineſſe, and how the benefit thereof may bee raiſed. The third is the habillity of the Inuentioner, to effect and performe his proiect propounded. The fourth is concerning the manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting or bargaining; In all which, I will endeauour to giue the beſt ſatisfaction that I may, out of the praecepts and grounds of this preſent Treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi> And therefore concerning the firſt point. The Tranſcript of his Maieſties moſt gratious grant and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge doth euidently ſhew and informe the Reader, that amongſt many other inuentions
<pb facs="tcp:18513:3"/>granted for one and thirty yeares, my Selfe, my Executors, Deputies and Aſſignes, may <hi>onely</hi> make, practiſe, and put in vſe, within any of his Maieſties Realmes and Dominions, the working, melting, and effecting of Iron, Steele, and other Mettles with Sea-coale, or Pit-coale. The principall end of which inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, that the Woods and Timber of our country might be ſaued, maintained and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from the great conſumption and waſte of our common Furnaces and Iron-Milnes, which as they are now ordinarily built and framed, can burne, ſpend, and conſume no other fewell but Char coale. The which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe if it may bee effected accordingly (as I make no doubt but by Gods bleſſing I ſhall) will prooue to bee the beſt and moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table buſineſſe and Inuention that euer was knowne or inuented in England theſe many yeares.</p>
            <p>For (to ſpeake nothing of the great benefit, and profit which may bee raiſed and made by twenty other Inuentions compriſed and
<pb facs="tcp:18513:3"/>comprehended vnder the Pattent) the yearly vallew of this mettle-buſineſſe alone, will amount vnto 330. thouſand pounds, <hi>per annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> after the ſecond or third yeare, as appeareth by this calculation.</p>
            <div type="calculation">
               <head>A Calculation ſhewing how the <hi>Mettle Inuention</hi> or Art, which maketh all kinde of Mettles or Metalique ſubstance, with Pit-coale or Sea-coale, will bee worth <hi>per annum. 330.</hi> thouſand pounds, immediatly after the two firſt yeares, which are the allotted times for Tryalls and Conformities, without any charges, (except the charges of Tryalls) to the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees, Partners, Aſsiſtants, and Dealers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are planted already in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Wales, eight hundred Milnes for the making of Iron, for there are foure hundred Milnes in Surry, Kent, &amp; Suſſex,
<pb facs="tcp:18513:4"/>as the towneſmen of Haſlemore haue teſtified and numbred vnto mee, there are alſo 200. Milnes in Wales, and 20. in Nottingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, as the Author hath beene credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>Now wee may well ſuppoſe, that all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland and Ireland (beſides the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named ſhires) will make vp the number of 180. Milnes more, being in all 800. Milnes.</p>
               <p>Moreouer one Milne alone ſpendeth year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Charcoale 500. pound and more, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe Clarkes and workmen in Iron buſineſſe, haue credibly teſtified, which in pit-coale will be done with the charges of 30. or 40. pounds, after the Inuentioners manner and inuention, or at the moſt with 50. pound, where carriage is farre and chargeable.</p>
               <p>So that this new Inuention in the 800. Iron milnes, will ſaue and gaine <hi>de claro</hi> the owners of thoſe milnes 320. thouſand pounds yearly, ouer and aboue their ordinary and annuall gaines, as it appeareth by this proportion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18513:4"/>
               <p> One Milne alone ſaueth yearely 400. li. <hi>Ergo,</hi> 800. Milnes ſaue yearly 320. thouſand pounds.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſaid <hi>Metalique</hi> inuention, beeing put and conuerted to Lead, Tinne, Copper, Braſſe, and Glaſſe-mettle, in all the ſeuerall Mineralls of England, Scotland, Ireland and Wales, will queſtionleſſe cleare yearely, by meanes of Fewell, aboue ten thouſand pounds more; ouer and beſides the ordinary gaines in the ſaid buſineſſe. So that the yearely Iron reuenues, added vnto theſe other <hi>Metalique</hi> reuenues, doe amount vnto 330. thouſand pounds, as was ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Now out of theſe <hi>Metalique</hi> gaines of 330. thouſand pounds yearely, the owners of the Milnes, Hearths, and Furnaces, may haue and receiue liberall rates and proportions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and allotted vnto them, ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their ordinary gaines, onely in lieu of conforming their Furnaces, Fineries and Chafferies to this Inuention of Pitt-coale
<pb facs="tcp:18513:5"/>and Earth-coale. And alſo the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, the Prince his Highneſſe, the Duke of Yorke, the Lord Vicount Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, and other parties interreſſed in the Pattent, may by their Compoſition and agreement with the ſaid Owners and Iron-Maiſters, yearely receiue, by way of rents and licences, the reſidew of that gaines which remaineth ouer and aboue that which was allotted and allowed to the Iron-Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for applying of this Inuention to their ordinary way of making of Iron, as more fully ſhall bee ſpecified, ſhewed, and prooued in the Apendix of this Treatiſe, which I am now preparing for the Printer and the Preſſe with all conuenient ſpeed.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice therefore, to giue the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſatisfaction, concerning the two firſt points, for the knowledge and the worth of the buſineſſes, and concerning the manner how certaine yearly annuities may bee raiſed to the dealers and aſſiſtants.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18513:5"/>
               <p> Now to perſwade the third point, that the Authour is able to effect the worke vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, in as ample manner as hee propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; wee plead and alledge as followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt the Inuentioner by his ſtudy, induſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and practiſe, hath already brought to paſſe and publiſhed diuerſe proiects and new deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, aſwell Litterall as Mechannicall, very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the common-wealth. His Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare Inuentions doe appeare and are knowne partly by his Printed Treatiſe of <hi>Dibere Adam,</hi> which is a Scholaſticall engin <hi>Aucomaton,</hi> and partly in diuerſe other Manuſcripts which he hath to ſhew. His new Mechanicks already performed, are to bee ſeene in the Inuentions which hee calleth by the names of <hi>Preſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, Wood-pleits, Ballance, Engin, Baramyha,</hi> and <hi>Hubla,</hi> of all which in priuate ſpeech hee is ready more largely to conferre, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their truth and goodneſſe at his Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes at Iſlington and Highbury. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.34. Thus <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth from the Beare and Lyon to Golyah the Gyant.</note> therefore he doubteth not but (by Gods bleſſing &amp; aſſiſtance, ſemblably with ſucceſſe)
<pb facs="tcp:18513:6"/>to effect his Inuention of Iron-works, as alſo al his other <hi>Metallique</hi> deuiſes and Inuentions, heere contained in the Patent, or Priuiledge of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly the conſideration of thinges in the like nature with it, are good inducements to perſwade vs well of this proiect, for Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making, Brewing, Dying, Caſting of Braſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, &amp;c. were (not many yeares ſince) done altogether with the fuell of wood and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coale; in ſtead whereof Sea-coale is now vſed as effectually and to as good vſe and purpoſe. Againe (that which is ſomewhat neerer the marke) the Blackſmith long agone forged all his Iron with Char-coale (as in ſome places where they are cheape they continue this courſe ſtill) but theſe many yeares ſmall Sea-coale hath, and doth ſerue the turne, as well and ſufficiently. Adde heerevnto, that very lately by a wind-Furnace, greene glaſſe, for windowes, is made as well with Pit-coale at Wincheſter houſe in Southwarke as it is done in other places with much waſt &amp; conſuming
<pb facs="tcp:18513:6"/>of infinite ſtore of Billetts and other Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuell.</p>
               <p>Thirdly the Inuention hath already experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and made tryall of the cheife particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar meanes and Inſtruments of diuers cheape waies of making of Irons in reall and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall moddles to him-ſelfe (though in ſmall things, according as his meanes would giue him leaue.) And this of his credit and honeſty he auoucheth and proteſteth: wherefore hee more confidently preſumeth to worke the ſame effects in grander Inſtruments and meanes of triall, after that hee hath receiued allowance of the dealers and aſſiſtants for it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly there can bee no doubt of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the matter propounded, if the Inuentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner can but make, or cauſe Sea-coale to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ſeruiceable for <hi>Metallique</hi> purpoſes as wood &amp; Char-coale is: The art and ſkill wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of conſiſteth cheifly in three points: The firſt is to bring Earth-coale to that equallity of heat that Wood or Char-coale hath; That is to ſay, that it make neither hotter nor coulder
<pb facs="tcp:18513:7"/>fier then the Wood or Char-coale doth: The ſecond meanes, is ſo to order and prepare Pit-coale, that all malignant proprieties, which are averſſe from the nature of Metallique ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, may bee extracted from it, or at leaſt deſtroyed in it: The third meanes is, the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and infuſion of thoſe deficient proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which as they are in Char-coale, ſo ought they to be found in Pit-coale.</p>
               <p>Now this three-fold miſtery and ſecret, the Author can certainly performe and atchieue, by the powerfull efficacie and meanes of his dexterous prerogatiue inſtruments, deuiſed for this purpoſe; as more at large is ſhewed, both in this Treatiſe, and in the Apendix, which very ſhortly ſhall come forth, and alſo ſhall be further confirmed and iuſtified by his dayly experiments and tryals, which hee will bee ready to ſhew to them whom they ſhall any wayes touch or concerne, or to them who are otherwiſe deſirous to aſſiſt and deale for the experimenting and accompliſhing of theſe ſo worthy good buſineſſes. And then
<pb facs="tcp:18513:7"/>alſo they ſhall know my purpoſe for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting</hi> and <hi>bargaining</hi> by word of mouth, as it is beſt fitting for priuate dealings and nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatings.</p>
               <p>And thus (hauing briefly touched theſe foure premiſed points) I conclude and ſhut vp this Preface of Metallica. Humbly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly beſeeching the Lord, who by his holy ſpirit inſpired * <hi>Bezaleel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Aholiab</hi> and * <hi>Hiram,</hi> with the light of Mechannicall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cro.</hi> 2.7.14.</note>
                  <hi>and in all manner of workemanſhip,</hi> for his effectuall bleſſings in theſe our enterpriſes,<note place="margin">Niſi dom. aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficauerit. Pſalm. <hi>127</hi>
                  </note>that that which was begun in his feare, may be proſecuted &amp; fully accompliſhed and built by his heauenly &amp; helpful hands, to the glory of his name, and for the good well-fare and emolument of the Kings moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, the Church and the Politicall eſtate wherein wee liue. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Simon Sturteuant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:8"/>
            <head>To the Reader, concerning the <hi>Errata.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO pretermit the correction of the leſſer literare faults, read and place, I pray you, the foure firſt lines. pag. 73. immediately before the 61. queſtion, for they are miſplaced.</p>
            <div type="errata">
               <head>Errata.</head>
               <p>Pag. 17. l. 12. 31. parts, <hi>for</hi> 33. parts. pag. 45. l. 11. Ignime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica, <hi>for</hi> In-ignimetallica. pa. 56. l. 17. Inſtruments <hi>for</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreuticks. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 21. Inſtrument, <hi>for</hi> Emporeutick. pa. 73. l. 13 conſiſteth, <hi>for</hi> conſiſting. pa. 76. l. 7. diuers meanes <hi>for</hi> diuers things. pag. 77. l. 11. bee incroached, <hi>for</hi> bee not incroached. pa. 93. l. 26. edge, <hi>for</hi> edge-toole. pa. 94. l. 3. fier, colouring, <hi>for</hi> fier-colouring. pa. 108. l. 10. alter-ſlagge, <hi>for</hi> after-ſlagge.</p>
               <p>In the Epiſtle to the Reader, in ſome copies, pag. 1. of A. l. 11. <hi>Dibere</hi> for <hi>Dibre.</hi> l. 12. <hi>Aucomaton,</hi> for <hi>Automa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> l. 18. <hi>Hubla,</hi> for <hi>Lubla.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18513:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18513:9"/>
            <head>Metallica.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAPVT. 1.</hi> The Tranſcript of his Maieſties Indenture.</head>
               <p>Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I vnderſtand, you haue promiſed and couenanted in your Pattent more fully and euidently to expreſse and enlarge in a Printed treatiſe, to be called</hi> Metalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, <hi>euery point and part of your priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged buſineſſe, to the intent that the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der might the better conceiue and iudge of the Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons propounded, and might the ſooner alſo bee induced to aſsiſt, and ſet forward, ſo good and worthy workes: First therefore I demand of you by what name and appellation you entitle that generall head, vnder the which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and comprehend all the ſeuerall Arts and Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your Pattent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> The generall, that comprehendeth all the other perticular Inuentions, is called <hi>Metallica,</hi> which is a word deriued and deduced from the Greeke and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18513:10"/>Latin words <hi>Metallon,</hi> and <hi>Metallum,</hi> which ſignifie, in Engliſh, Mettles, which properly are Minerall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, digged and taken out of the earth, of which ſort, are Iron, Lead, Tin, Copper, Braſſe, Gold, and Siluer, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>Doth your Pattent of</hi> Metallica, <hi>onely containe the making of mettles by the meanes of Sea-coale and Pit-coale, and with your other</hi> Metallicall <hi>inſtruments which you haue deuiſed for that purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. His Maieſties gratious grant is very large and ample, for it doth not onely comprehend and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the making of all kinde of mettles, after the manner preſcribed, but alſo equally authorizeth and licenſeth any other Mechanick inuentions compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended vnder the generall definition of <hi>Metallica</hi> which is mentioned in the Schedules or Manuſcript treatiſe annexed to the Pattent, which Schedules haue the ſame force and validitie as his Maieſties Indenture it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>Then that I may certainely know and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the extent of your priuiledge, repeate, I pray you, word by word, the definition of</hi> Metallica, <hi>as it is written in the ſaid Schedules, annexed to your Pattent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Metallica</hi> mentioned in the petition, is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined. <hi>Metallica</hi> is an Art or Inuention, ſhewing how diuerſe things and Materials, now made and atteined vnto, in a very chargeable ſort, after the ordinary way, may be made and atteined to after a more chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per manner, and as with the helpe of common inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: ſo more eſpecially by diuerſe new deuiſed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18513:10"/>
                  <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments and meanes.</p>
               <p>From theſe <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, the Art is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally called <hi>Metallica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 4. <hi>This ſummary definition giueth mee ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall light and vnderſtanding into your buſineſſes, but that I may bee the more fully ſatisfied, I pray you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe alſo the tenour of his Maieſties grant, as it is vnder the broad ſeale of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="royal_blazon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18513:11"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                        <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter_patent">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18513:11"/>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>James R.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Indenture made, the xxix. day of February, in the yeares of the Reigne of our Soueraigne Lord <hi>Iames,</hi> by the grace of God, King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. of England, France and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land the ninth, &amp; of Scotland the xlv. Betwene our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, of the one party, and <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> Gentleman of the other party. WHEREAS the ſaid <hi>Simon Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuant,</hi> by long his ſtudy &amp; great charge, hath atteined vnto diuerſe new exact Mechanick Arts, Myſteries, Waies and Secrets of his own Inuention, whereby all kind of mettles, works, and other things and materialls, as namely Irons, Steeles, Leads, Tins, Coppers, Braſſes, and ſuch like. Secondly all kind of Metalique concoctions, as Sand-mettles, Aſh-mettles, Ammels, and ſuch like. Thirdly, all kinde of Burnt-earths, as Tiles, Pauing-ſtones, Bricks, and ſuch like. Fourthly all kind of Preſ-wares, as Preſt-tiles, Preſt-bricks, Preſt-monions,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18513:12"/>Preſt-ſtones and ſuch like, with diuerſe other things and materials now made after the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie courſe, with Wood-fewell and Char-coale, may be aſwell made, wrought, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> affirmeth, with Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale, and Bruſh-fewell, whereby the Woods now gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally waſted, in all the chiefe wood-land coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of this realme of England by Iron milnes, and ſuch other Metallicall Furnaces and hearths, may be preſerued from the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption thereof, and ſaued from like incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience in other his Maieſties dominions, all which premiſſes, ſo by this new Inuention to be made, the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, ſhall be in ſubſtance and for vſe as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and as good as the other like Materialls now made and wrought with the chargeable and exceſſiue waſte of Wood and Char-cole. AND whereas alſo the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> for the better making, working, effecting, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, burning, melting and effecting, the ſaid mettals, workes, things, and Materialls, by and wth Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18513:12"/>Bruſh-fewell, hath by his ſaid Inuention and skill, inuented diuers Furnaces, hearths, teſts, tooles, engins, milnes, and other inſtruments and meanes, new, and of his owne Inuention, neuer heretofore vſed or put in practiſe by any other. And hath alſo by his ſaid Inuentions and skill, attained to the knowledge how to vſe and imploy diuerſe other common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, to the making, working, and effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid mettles, workes, materialls, and things, which other common inſtruments haue bin heretofore, and are vſed in other arts, ſciences, and manuell occupations, but were not, nor haue bin as yet conuerted, vſed, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, to, for, or about the making, working, effecting, &amp; producing the ſaid mettels, works, materials and things: which ſaid skil &amp; Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſaid <hi>S. Sturteuant,</hi> &amp; the ſaid mettles, workes, things, and other Materials, and the meanes and inſtruments whereby to worke and effect the ſame, are in ſome meaſure men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and expreſſed in the Schedule or Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules, to theſe preſents annexed, and ſhall bee more fully, amply, and perticularly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18513:13"/>ſpecified, deſcribed, and conteined in a large treatiſe, which the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> hath already conceiued, and ſhall bee put in Print, and ſo publiſhed before the laſt day of Eaſter terme next enſuing the date hereof, which Treatiſe ſo to bee Printed, ſhall be inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>A Treatiſe of Metallica:</hi> which ſaid Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſaid <hi>Simon,</hi> may and will prooue beneficiall to the common-wealth, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the abundant plenty of the ſaid things and materials which it daily will bring forth, as alſo becauſe it ſaueth and preſerueth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Timber, Char-coale, Wood-fewell, and other things and commodities waſtefully conſumed and ſpent, the generall want where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of already is felt. AND, for aſmuch as our ſaid Soueraigne Lord is giuen to vnderſtand, that this art, skill, induſtrie and inuentions of the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> of making, caſting, founding, working, and acquiring of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid mettles, workes of Iron, materials, &amp; things by Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale and Bruſh-fewell, and all and euery, or any of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18513:13"/>them, and alſo the making of the ſaid new deuiſed engins, hearths, furnaces, and other meanes and inſtruments, and the imploying of the ſaid inſtruments, vſed in other ſciences and Arts, to the making, working, effecting, and producing the ſaid Mettales and other workes, materials and things, is a thing not yet practiſed nor brought into any trade, occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or myſterie, within any of his kingdomes, but is an Inuention in ſubſtance new, and which ſhall not preiudice or croſſe any from priuiledge or grant by his Maieſtie heretofore made or granted vnder the great ſeale of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for the vſing and making of any former Inuention, and therefore fit to bee priuiledged for a certain time, the rather for that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conceiueth, that the ſaid inuentions and skils, may and will become profitable and good for the common-wealth of theſe realms, and alſo augment his cuſtomes and impoſt, in regard it bringeth forth great and aboundant ſtore of the aforeſaid Materials and things, not onely for the vſe of his Highneſſe realmes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18513:14"/>and dominions heere at home, but alſo for trafficke and Marchandize into forraine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries abroad, which are cuſtomeable. In regard whereof and alſo for, and in conſideration of the good, faithful and acceptable ſeruices heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore done and performed vnto his ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, by the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> As alſo to the end that the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſome conuenient recompence, benefit and profit for his ſaid ſeruices, as alſo for his ſtudies, laboures and charges in perfecting theſe Inuentions, to the Common good, which may enſue heereby to his Highnes Realmes and Dominions. THIS INDENTVRE WITNESSETH that our ſaid ſoueraigne Lord the King, of his eſpeciall grace, certaine knowledge and meere motion, and of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue royal, hath giuen and granted, and by theſe preſents for him, his heires and ſucceſſors doth giue and grant, vnto the ſaid <hi>Simon Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and his, and their Deputy and Deputies the ſole, full, abſolute and free power, liberty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18513:14"/>and authority, to make, worke, produce, acc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and bring forth, all kinde of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid mettles, and other the materials, and things, by, and with Sea-coale, Pitt-coale, Earth-coale, Bruſh-fewell, and all, euery, or any of them, in all parts and places of his Maieſties realmes of England, Scotland, Ireland, and Wales, and alſo within all the ſame places and dominions, to make, frame, erect, acquire, and prouide, or cauſe to bee made, framed, erected, acquired, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, all neceſſary Inſtruments and meanes. As namely, all Worke-houſes, Furnaces, Hearths, Milnes, Structures, Engins, Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Teſts, Tooles, Inſtruments, Deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or things of Iron, or other ſtuffe or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whatſoeuer, which are already in vſe, in any other trade, myſterie, arte, or occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as yet not exerciſed or vſed, in, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the making, working, caſting, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, acquiring, and producing of the ſayd mettles and other materialls and things, for, and to the end and purpoſe aforeſaid, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18513:15"/>to make, worke and effect the ſaid mettles, and other materials, and things, by, and with Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale and Bruſh-fewel, and all, euery, or any of them. And alſo in all the ſaid places and dominions, to make, frame and erect, vſe, and imploy, or cauſe to be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and erected all the ſaid new Furnaces, hearths, deuiſes, inſtruments and meanes, which are meerely of the new Inuention of the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> to, for, in, or about the making, working, caſting, founding, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, and producing of the ſaid mettles, and other the ſaid Materials and things, and to all or any other purpoſe or purpoſes vſe or vſes, whatſoeuer, in as ample ſort and manner as they or any of them are deſcribed, expreſſed, or mentioned in the Schedule to theſe preſents annexed, or ſhall be more fully demonſtrated, ſpecified, or mentioned in the Treatiſe of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica,</hi> which ſhall bee as aforeſaid Printed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt day of Eaſter Terme next enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. AND our ſaid Soueraigne Lord doth further by theſe preſents, for him, his heires, &amp; ſucceſſors, aſſigne, appoint, ordaine, conſtitute,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18513:15"/>licence and authoriſe the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators, and aſſignes, to haue the ſole power, liberty, and authority, by and with Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale, and Bruſh-fewell, and all, euery, or any of them, and by his ſaid Inuentions, arts, and skills in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented and deuiſed for the making of all kinds of the ſaid mettles, and other the Materials and things, and alſo for the making, framing, and erecting of all ſuch Inſtruments and meanes, as Worke-houſes, Furnaces, Milnes, Quernes, Structures, Engins, Veſſels, Tooles, Inſtruments, Deuiſes, and things heretofore vſed in any other Arts or Sciences, to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed or vſed in or about the making, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or producing the ſaid mettals, things, and materials, or any of them, as aforeſaid, and alſo to haue the ſole power, liberty, and authority, for the making, framing, erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or producing of all the ſaid new deuiſes, inſtruments, and meanes <hi>Metallicall,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, in what ſort, or about what thing ſoeuer the ſame or any of them ſhall bee vſed or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: and that the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18513:16"/>executors, adminiſtrators, aſſignes, and his &amp; their deputy &amp; deputies, &amp; none other, without his, or their ſpeciall licence or tolleration, ſhal or may make any kind, or kinds of the ſaid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, &amp; other the materials &amp; things, by, or with ſea-coale, pit-coale, earth-coale, &amp; bruſhfewel, or al, ſome, or any of them, by means of, or by vſing &amp; imploying the ſaid Inuentions of the ſaid <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or any part or parcel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or make, frame &amp; erect, any the ſaid work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, furnaces, hearths, milnes, ſtructures, engins, teſts, veſſels, tooles, inſtruments, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; things heretofore vſed, in any other arts, or ſciences, which by the ſaid inuentions of the ſaid <hi>Simon,</hi> ſhalbe tranſferred or conuerted, or turned to be vſed, exerciſed &amp; imployed, in, or about the making, caſting, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, working, acquiring and producing of the ſaid mettles or materials, things and deuiſes, by, or with Sea-coale, earth-coale, pit-coale, and bruſh-fewell, or all, ſome, or any of them, or to make, frame, or erect, any of the ſaid new deuiſed inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and means of the ſaid <hi>Simon,</hi> either to the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, caſting, working, or effecting, all or any the ſaid works, metles, or materials, by or with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18513:16"/>ſea-coale, earth-coale, and bruſh-fewell, or all, ſome, or any of them, or to any other end or purpoſe whatſoeuer. TO haue and to hold, vſe, exerciſe and enioy, the ſole making, caſting, founding, working, tempering, acquiring, and producing of all and euery the ſaid mettles, and other the ſaid premiſes, in maner &amp; forme afor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and to the end &amp; purpoſes aforeſaid, vnto the ſaid <hi>S. Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and aſſignes, and by his and their deputy &amp; deputies, for &amp; during the time and terme of 31. yeares, now next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, immediatly from &amp; after the date of theſe preſents. Yeelding, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring &amp; paying therefore, yearly &amp; euery yeare immediatly, from, and after the date hereof, for, and during the ſaid terme of 31. yeares, to our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, his heires and ſucceſſors, at the receipt of his Highneſſe Exchequer at Weſtmin. alwaies in the terme of <hi>S. Michael,</hi> ten parts of ſuch ſum or ſums of money, and other cleare yeerely profits, in 33. parts to be deuided, as he the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturtenant,</hi> his executors, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators, or aſſignes, ſhall yearely haue or receiue, during the ſaid terme of one and thirty years, by way of compoſition or otherwiſe, for,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18513:17"/>or by making, framing, or erecting, caſting, founding, and acquiring, or otherwiſe, for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſing or authoriſing any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, to make, frame, caſt, erect, found, or acquire, any of the ſaid Materialls, Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Furnaces, Hearths, Milnes, Stuctures, Engins, Veſſels, Teſts, Tooles, Inſtruments, deuiſes, and things aforeſaid, The charges and expences in and about the ſame, and euery of them, expended out of the ſaid thirty three parts, alwaies deducted and allowed to the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators and aſſignes, And likewiſe yeelding, rendring, and paying, vnto the moſt excellent Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> eldeſt ſonne of our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornewall, and Earle of Cheſter, &amp; his executors or admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators, yearly and euery yeare, during the ſaid terme of one and thirty yeares, in the ſame termes of Saint <hi>Michaell</hi> fiue parts of the ſaid ſumme and ſummes of money, and other cleere profits in thirty three parts to bee deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to bee alwayes paid and deliuered to ſuch
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18513:17"/>perſon or perſons as the ſaid moſt excellent Prince ſhall appoint to receiue the ſame, at his highneſſe Pallace of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Middleſex. And alſo yeelding, rendring, and paying vnto the moſt high and mightie Prince <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of Yorke; ſecond Sonne of our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, vnto his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and adminiſtrators during the ſaid terme of thirty one yeares in the ſame tearmes of Saint <hi>Michaell</hi> the Arch-angell, two parts of the ſaid ſumme and ſummes of mony and other cleare profits afore ſaid in 31 parts to be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be alwaies paid and deliuered, at the ſaid Pallace of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> to ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as our ſaid Soueraine Lord the King, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Mynority of the ſaid Duke of Yorke, and after his full age hee the ſaid Duke ſhall appoint to receiue the ſame: And moreouer yeelding, rendring, and paying vnto <hi>Robert</hi> Vicount Rocheſter Baron of Wainick his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors and adminiſtrators in the ſame termes of Saint <hi>Michaell</hi> and at the ſaid, Pallace of S. <hi>Iames</hi> one part of the ſaid ſum and ſums of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18513:18"/>money, and other cleere parts to be deuided. AND as concerning the reſidue of the ſaid ſumme and ſums of money, and other cleere profits to be deuided, it ſhall and may bee law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to, and for, the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors, adminiſtrators, and aſſignes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and keepe one part thereof to his or their owne propper vſe and vſes, and for the other fourteene yearely partes of the ſaid thirty three partes of the ſaid yeerely ſumme and ſummes of money, and other cleere yearely profits; It ſhall, and may be lawfull, to, and for the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturtenant,</hi> his executors, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators, and aſſignes, at his, and their diſcretion, and in ſuch manner and forme, and by ſuch rates and proportions, as he, and they, ſhall in their diſcretions thinke meet to diſpoſe thereof and to expend and diſtribute the ſame, and euery part and parcell thereof, amongſt ſuch perſon, or perſons, as ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, ioyne, be aſiſting, aiding or helping to the aduancing, or ſetting forwards of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18513:18"/>workes and inuentions afore-ſaid, or any of them, and amongſt ſuch perſon or perſons as ſhal be owners of the ſaid work-houſes, furna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hearthes, milnes, ſtructures, engine, veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, teſts, tooles, inſtruments, deuiſes, and things before mentioned, or any of them.</p>
                  <p>And the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> for him, his heires, executors, adminiſtrators, and aſſignes and for euery of them, doth couenant, and grant, by theſe preſents, to, and with, our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, his heires, and ſucceſſors, that he the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators, or aſſignes, ſhal, and wil, yearely and euery yeare, during the ſaid terme of one and thirty yeares, well and truely yeeld, render, ſatiſfie, content and pay, or cauſe to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented and payed, the ſaid tenne partes of the ſaid cleere profits, in maner and forme afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, vnto our Soueraigne Lord, his Heires, and Succeſſors, and ſhall, and will like-wiſe, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the aforeſaid Terme of one and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares, well and truly yeeld, render, ſatiſfie,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18513:19"/>content and pay vnto the ſaid Prince of Wales, his executors or adminiſtrators the ſaid fiue parts of the ſaid cleere proffits, in manner and forme afore-ſaid, And alſo to the ſaid Duke his executors or adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors the ſaid two parts of the ſaid cleere prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits in manner and forme afore-ſaid, And alſo to the ſaid Lord Vicount Rocheſter, his executors or adminiſtrators the ſaid one part of the cleere proffits in manner and forme as the ſame one part is formerly in theſe preſents apointed to bee yeelded, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and payed to the ſaid Lord Vicount Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, his executors and adminiſtrators; AND for aſmuch as when the ſaid skill, worke, and Inuentions of the ſaid <hi>Simon Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuant,</hi> which hee by his great induſtry, coſt and expences hath attained to, ſhall appeare and bee made commonly knowne, it is very likely that many perſons will without the priuity of the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, adminiſtrators or aſſignes, make, frame,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18513:19"/>and erect the like, and peraduenture hauing his Platforme, adde therevnto ſome further new inuention for their gaines, or otherwiſe put the ſame in practiſe at their pleaſure, and make the ſaid mettles, and other materials and premiſes aforeſaid, thereby reaping the fruits of the labours of the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> and ſo defraud, both our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, and the ſaid Prince, and the ſaid Duke of Yorke, and the ſaid Lord Vicount Rocheſter, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators and aſſignes, and ſuch others, as ſhall aduenture therein, of a great part of the benefit and profit which might otherwiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew vnto our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, and to the ſaid moſt excellent Prince, and Duke of Yorke, and to the ſaid other parties by ſuch skill, worke, and Inuention aforeſaid. Our ſaid Soueraigne Lord therfore, fauouring the good endeuours and ſtudies of the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant</hi> in the premiſſes, and his former ſeruice done vnto his Highneſſe, for him, his heires and ſucceſſors, for the better encouraging of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18513:20"/>him the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators and aſſignes, in the ſame, and the better to enable him to vnder-goe and beare the burthen and charge thereof, and to auoide all deceipt that any way may hinder our ſaid Soueraigne Lord, or the ſaid moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince, or Duke of Yorke, or any of the ſaid parties aforeſaid, doth by theſe preſents declate and ſignifie, that his Maieſties Royall will and pleaſure is, and our ſaid Soueraigne Lord doth hereby ſtreightly will, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, all, and euery perſon or perſons, of what ſtate, degree, or condition ſoeuer, that they, nor any of them, during the ſaid terme of one and thirty yeares, ſhall not preſume or attempt, by any arte, deuiſe, skill, or cunning, directly or indirectly, without the ſpeciall licence, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and conſent of him the ſaid <hi>Simon Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, or of his, or their deputie, or deputies, there-vnto by him, or them lawfully authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to make, frame, erect, contriue, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme any kinde, or kindes of the aforeſaid
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18513:20"/>mettles, and the other Materialls and things, or any of them, by, or with Sea-coale, Pit-coale, Earth-coale and Bruſh-fewell, or all, ſome, or any of them, by all, or any the ſaid Inuentions, or meanes, inuented or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed by the ſaid <hi>Simon,</hi> or by vſing or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing any part, or parcell of the ſame, or to vtter, or ſell the ſaid mettles, or other mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, or things ſo made, framed, or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or any of them, or to make, frame, worke, erect, vſe or imploy, within any the ſaid Realmes and Dominions of our ſaid So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lord the King, any ſuch or the like engins, inſtruments, or workes heretofore vſed in any other Artes or Sciences, for, or to the making, founding, or effecting the ſaid mettles, things and materials, by and with Sea-coale, Pitt-coale, Earth-coale, and Bruſh-fewell, and all, or any of them, or any of the ſayd new deuiſed Inſtruments and things, either too, or about the making or working the ſaid mettles, things, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18513:21"/>materials, as aforeſaid, or to any end or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe whatſoeuer, or to make or doe, any act or thing, whereby, or by meanes whereof, our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the King, or the ſaid moſt excellent Prince of Wales, or the ſaid Duke of Yorke, or the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators or aſſignes, or other the ſaid parties, ſhall or may ſuſtaine any preiudice, loſſe or detriment, in the ſaid Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or workes, or in any profit or commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which they, or any of them, may or might otherwiſe haue, receiue, or enioy, by meanes of the ſame inuentions or workes, or any of them, vpon paine of the high diſpleaſure of our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the King, and vpon paine of impriſonment of their bodies, and forfeitures of all, and euery the ſaid materials, inſtruments, and things aforeſaid, which ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be wrought, framed, or made, by any perſon or perſons, contrary to the tenour of theſe preſents, and Royall prohibition therein, with ſuch further penalties, paines, and forfeitures, as by the laws and ſtatutes of the ſaid Realms,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18513:21"/>can, or may be inflicted, vpon them, or any of them, for their wilfull and obſtinate diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and contempt of his Highneſſe ſaid commandement and prerogatiue Royall. And if it ſhall happen that any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, contemptuouſly neglecting this his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties will and pleaſure, in theſe preſents decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, after notice therof giuen, ſhall make or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any kind or kinds of the afore-ſaid met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and other the materials and things, by, or with Sea-cole, Pit-coale, Eearth-coale &amp; Bruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuell, or all, ſome, or any of them, by any of the ſaid meanes and Inuentions, or any part or parcell of them or any of them, or ſhall frame, worke, erect, vſe or imploy any ſuch or the like engins, inſtruments, tooles, imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or workes, for, and to the purpoſe and purpoſes aforeſaid, the ſame, and all, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them ſhall bee taken and ſeized, by the Conſtable or other officer, dwelling neereſt thereunto, to, and for the only vſe and behoofe of our ſaid ſoueraigne Lord the King, his heires and ſucceſſors, AND further our ſaid ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18513:22"/>Lord the King of his more abundant grace, certaine knowledge and meere motion doth by theſe preſents for him, his heires and ſucceſſors, giue and grant full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, adminiſtrators, and aſſignes, and his and their Deputy and Deputies and euery of them with the aſſiſtance of a Conſtable, Tithing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Headborough, or any other ordinary officer in any Citty, towne, place, or places, as well within the liberties as without, within the ſaid Realmes and Dominions, at all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery time and times, to haue acceſſe and entry into any houſe, place, and places, where ſuch mettles and other the premiſſes ſhall be made and wrought or otherwiſe layd vp contrary to his Maieſties grant, and there to ſearch, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, and ſee, that during the ſaid terme of 31. yeares, no manner of ſuch or the like Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, workes, or practizes, of making, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, any kind, or kinds, of the ſaid mettles and other the premiſſes to be made, wrought, ſould, vſed, or imployed, within the ſaid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18513:22"/>Realms contrary to the true meaning of theſe preſents, and by all lawfull and conuenient waies and meanes to ſearch, ſee examine and find out, all offences during the ſayd time that ſhall bee committed contrary to any guift, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, authority, commandement, prohbiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or other thing in theſe preſents mentioned, ſpecified, and to ſeaze, as aforeſaid, ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and other things whatſoeuer, made, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or erected, vſed, exerciſed or occupied contrary to the true intent of theſe preſents or any clauſe heerin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained. And his Highneſſe will and pleaſure is, and by theſe preſents for him, his heires and ſucceſſors, his Maieſty doth ſtreightly charge and command all Iuſtices of peace, Maiors, Sherifs, Bailifes, Conſtables and al other Officers, miniſters and ſubiects of his Highneſſe, his heires and ſucceſſors for the time being, that they and euery of them, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaid terme of 31. yeares, or the dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate exemplification or the enrolement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhal be aiding &amp; aſiſting to the ſaid <hi>S. Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuant,</hi> his executors, adminiſtrators, aſſignes &amp; deputies &amp; euery of them in the due execution
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18513:23"/>of all and euery the ſaid grants, authorities, commandements, licences, priuiledges, inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions, prohibitions, and euery other thing in theſe preſents mentioned and ſpecified, or any of them. PROVIDED alwayes, that this Indenture, nor any thing therein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhall extend, or be conſtrued to extend, to reſtraine or hinder any perſon or perſons, for vſing, or exerciſing any their owne Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Artes heretofore exerciſed, put in vſe, and priuiledged, by any his Maieſties Letters Partents, heeretofore made and granted to them or any of them, but that it ſhall, and may be lawfull, to and for all and euery the ſaid perſon or perſons, to exerciſe, vſe, and put in practiſe all and euery the ſaid inuentions heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore practized, put in vſe, excerciſed, and priuiledged by any of the ſaid Letters Pattents, to them, or any of them, made or granted, in as ample ſort, and manner, as they might, or may, exerciſe, practiſe, or vſe the ſame, if theſe preſents had neuer beene had, or made any in theſe preſents to the contrary notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18513:23"/>IN WITNES whereof, to the one part of theſe Indentures remaining with the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> our ſaid Soueraigne Lord the Kings Maieſtie, hath cauſed the great Seale of England to bee put, and to the other part thereof remaining with our ſaid Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord the King, the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturtenant</hi> hath put his ſeale. Yeouen the day and yeare firſt aboue written.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Exam. <hi>Henry Hubbert.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="summary">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18513:24"/>
                  <head>The Docquet to the Pattent.</head>
                  <p>THis is your Maieſties part of the Indentures, whereby your Highneſſe doth grant, licence, and priuiledge vnto <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. That bee, his executors, deputies, and aſsignes onely, and none other, ſhall and may, during the terme of <hi>31.</hi> yeares, make, practiſe, and put in vſe, within any your Maieſties Realmes and dominions, certaine Inuentions, Furnaces, and Inſtruments, deuiſed and inuented by himſelfe, for the working, and effecting with Sea-coale, Pitt-coale, Earth-coale, and Bruſh-fewell, diuers things and workes heretofore done with Wood-fewell, as namely Irous, Steeles, Leads, Tinnes, Coppers, Braſſes, Glaſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettles, Mines, Tiles, Bricks, Potter-ware, and ſuch like. And there is reſerued to your Maieſtie vpon this grant, ten parts in thirty three parts, to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided of the cleare yearely profits that ſhall bee made by the ſaid new Inuentions: and to the Prince his Highneſſe, fiue ef thoſe parts: and to the Duke
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18513:24"/>of Yorke two of thoſe parts, and to the Lord Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Rochester, one of thoſe parts; and to the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> one other of thoſe parts, and to the disburſers of the moneys for the tryall and effecting of the ſaid Inuentions, foureteene ſuch parts, and the declaration and diſcouering of this Inuention, is partly ſet down in a certaine ſckedule, which is to bee annexed to theſe Indentures. And the full and plaine manifeſtation thereof is to bee ſett forth in Print, by the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant,</hi> before the last day of Easter terme next, and conteineth a <hi>prouiſo,</hi> that this new grant ſhall not croſſe any former grant, hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made to any others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="witnesses">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18513:25"/>
                  <div type="witness">
                     <p>
                        <hi>And is done vpon ſignification giuen vnto mee by</hi> Chriſtopher Perkins, <hi>Knight, of your Maieſties good pleaſure in that behalfe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Exam.</hi> Henry Hubbert.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="witness">
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is his Maieſties pleaſure, that theſe doe paſſe by immediate warrant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Robert Salisbury.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Receiued 29. of February 1611.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="witness">
                     <p>
                        <hi>An Indenture betweene the Kings Maieſtie, and</hi> S. Sturteuant.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>COPPIN.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18513:25"/>
               <head>The Manuſcript Treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi> CAPVT. 2.</head>
               <p>Reader.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Tranſcript of his Maieſties Indenture, which you haue rehearſed, there is further referrence vnto a manuſcript Treatiſe, or certaine ſchedules which are annexed vnto the grant, which I pray you alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe vnto mee, according to the Tenour of the words in the originall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. The manuſcript Treatiſe of</hi> Metallica, <hi>which otherwiſe is termed by the names of ſchedules in the Indenture, is comprehended in theſe ten Sections fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 1. Metallica,</hi> the generall of all Metallicall Arts.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Etallica,</hi> mentioned in the petition, is thus defined.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Metallica</hi> is an Art or Inuention, ſhewing how diuers things and mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, now made and atteined vnto in a very chargeable ſort, after the ordinary way, may be made and attained vnto after a more cheaper manner, and as with the help of common inſtruments, ſo more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18513:26"/>eſpecially by diuers new deuiſed <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and meanes, as in the printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica,</hi> more at large ſhall bee mentioned and expreſſed.</p>
                  <p>From theſe <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments the Art is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally called <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The doctrine of <hi>Metallica</hi> cannot diſtinctly be known or methodically expreſſed, except that the Art which preſcribeth precepts, general to all Arts &amp; inuentions called <hi>Heuretica</hi> be firſt precognized.</p>
                  <p>R. Define Heuretica.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Heuretica</hi> is the Art of inuentions, teaching how to find out new, and to iudge of the old, and ſo forth, as followeth in the printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Metallica,</hi> thus generally deſcribed is of two ſorts, <hi>Ignemetallica,</hi> which worketh with fire and hearth, or <hi>Inignemetallica,</hi> which vſeth not the meanes of fire, for to attaine to the thing or materiall intended, yet it vſeth the other <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments, wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it is called more propperly <hi>Metallorganica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignemetallica,</hi> comprehendeth many generall inuenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, which are reduced into theſe 7. heads, firſt <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica, propriae dicta,</hi> ſecondly <hi>Preſſoria,</hi> thirdly <hi>Terrica,</hi> fourthly <hi>Hydrelica,</hi> fiftly <hi>Hydrometallica,</hi> ſixtly <hi>Hydro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſoria,</hi> ſeauenthly <hi>Hydroterrica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 2.</hi> Metallica proprié dicta.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MEtallica,</hi> in the propper and ſtrict ſignification is thus defined.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18513:26"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Metallica</hi> is an Ignick inuention, for the cheaper making of all kindes of mettles or Metalique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctures, by the meanes of cheape firing, and other <hi>Metallical,</hi> inſtruments, wherevpon the materials and things made by this Arte, are called <hi>Metaliques.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The contents of Metallica,</hi> proprie dicta, <hi>in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Materials which the Art maketh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talique Materials are as
<list>
                        <item>1. All kind of Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles as
<list>
                              <item>1. Prepared or roaſted oares, Mine-ſtones, or Mettle-ſtones beeing the fitt matter of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallique</hi> liquours.</item>
                              <item>2. Irons, Steeles.</item>
                              <item>3. Leads.</item>
                              <item>4. Tins.</item>
                              <item>5. Coppers, braſſes.</item>
                              <item>6. Any other new kind of met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, which may hereafter bee found beeing made and wrought after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his manner and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention.</item>
                              <item>7. All compounded mettles of the ſame kind, as Pewters, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettles, Sodars, Candle-ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettle, beeing made and wrought after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his manner and Inuention.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18513:27"/>
                        <item>All kind of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talique concoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creats, as
<list>
                              <item>1. All kinde of Sand-mettles, or Aſh-mettles.</item>
                              <item>2. All kind of Ammels, Beugles, or ſuch commixtures.</item>
                              <item>3. All kind of Metallique ſlagges or cinders, if (perhaps) they may be turned to ſome profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vſe.</item>
                              <item>4. Other compounds of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named concoctures, beeing made and wrought after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Inuention.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall be further mentioned and enlarged in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 3.</hi> Metallicall Inſtruments.</head>
                  <p>THe Inſtruments and meanes <hi>Metallicall,</hi> which are vſed for the producing of metallique mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls or things, are of two ſorts, common or peculiar.</p>
                  <p>The common inſtruments are ſuch which are bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from other trades, occupations and myſteries, amongſt which wee haue eſpecially vſe of Ioyners, Smiths, Turners, not onely of their Inſtruments and Tooles, but alſo of their Emporeuticks which they ordinarily make, as Preſſes, Vices, Screwes, Bellowes, Tongs, &amp;c. made either of Iron and Wood, or of both together.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18513:27"/>
                  <p> The peculiar inſtruments are thoſe that are of the Authors Inuention, beeing of chiefe and principall vſe, for the working of <hi>Metallicall</hi> effects.</p>
                  <p>The peculiar Inſtruments of inuention, are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally of three ſorts, Lenick, Plegnick and Caminick.</p>
                  <p>Lenicks are peculiar <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, which worke their opperation and effect by preſſing, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſioning, or moulding, and that either by thruſting or drawing.</p>
                  <p>All the kindes of theſe Lenick inſtruments, are at large deſcribed in the doctrine of the arte <hi>Preſsoria,</hi> which is part of the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is great vſe of theſe Lenick inſtruments, for the tempering and commixing of Sea-coale and Stone-coale.</p>
                  <p>Plegnicks are peculiar <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, which performe their opperation and effect, by their dexterous and artificiall ioynt-moouing.</p>
                  <p>All the kinds of Plegnick inſtruments, are at large deſcribed in the doctrine of the arte <hi>Plegnica,</hi> which is part of the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is great vſe of the Plegnick inſtruments for the making of Eumechanick and reformed Milnes &amp; Bellowſes.</p>
                  <p>Caminicks are peculiar <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, which performe their opperation and effect, by the new kind of Furnacing and Hearthing.</p>
                  <p>All the kinds of Caminick inſtruments, are at large deſcribed in the doctrine of the art <hi>Caminica,</hi> which is part of the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18513:28"/>
                  <p> The inſtruments <hi>Metallicall,</hi> although they are of cheefe vſe in all the <hi>Metallicall</hi> arts, yet are they more peculiarly belonging to <hi>Metallica, proprie dicta,</hi> and for this cauſe they are anexed to it.</p>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall be further mentioned, and inlarged in the printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 4.</hi> Preſſoria.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PReſſoria</hi> is a kind of Ignick Inuention, which by the meanes of cheape fiering, and by other <hi>Metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall</hi> Inſtruments and meanes, maketh all kinds of Preſſ-wares or Mould-wares.</p>
                  <p>Preſſ-ware or Mould-ware is any thing that can bee made, wrought, or formed of clay and earth, not by hand, and the round table (as the Potters vſe) but by Preſſe and Mould, or by preſſing and moulding, and that by the help of <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments and meanes.</p>
                  <p>There be many ſorts and kindes of Preſſ-wares by reaſon of different figures and diuers vſes vnto which they are to be applied, all which kindes are reduced to theſe two heades of Rude-ware and Poliſht ware.</p>
                  <p>Rude-ware are ſuch ſorts of Preſſ-ware, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are preſſed and moulded, require no further ornament; as Preſt-pipes, Preſt-tiles, Preſt-brickes, Preſt-ſtones: and ſuch like, expreſſed in the printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:18513:28"/>
                  <p> Polliſht-ware, are ſuch ſorts of Preſſ-wares, which after they are preſſed and moulded, doe receiue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ornament or beauty, as preſt-monions for win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and preſt-columnes, and ſuch like, deſcribed in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo ſorth, as it ſhall bee further mentioned and enlarged in the printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 5. <hi>Terrica.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>TErrica</hi> is an Ignick inuention, for the cheaper making of all kinds of Burnt-earths, by meanes of <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, wherevpon the Materialls made by this Art, are called <hi>Terricks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The contents of Terrica, in the ſeuer all Materialls which the Art maketh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Terrick Materials, are all kinde of burnt-earth, as
<list>
                        <item>1. All bricks burnt or baked, after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his manner and inuention, though made and moulded according to common order of Brick-makers.</item>
                        <item>2. All kinde of Tiles burnt or baked, after the ſaid <hi>S. Surteuant</hi> his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and inuention, though made, and moulded according to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon order of Tile-making.</item>
                        <item>3. All kind of Potter-ware, burnt or baked after the ſaid <hi>S. Sturteu.</hi> his maner &amp; Inuention, though mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded according to common order.</item>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18513:29"/>
                        <item>4. All kinde of limes, plaiſters, alla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſters burnt, after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his manner and Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                        <item>5. All kinde of Way-ſtones, Way-grauels, Way-earths, burnt and made after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant</hi> his manner and Inuention, This arte is called <hi>Itineraria.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. Laſtly, any other kinde of burnt-earths, that here-after may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, as good and profitable for the common-wealth, being made, burnt, and wrought, after the ſaid <hi>Simon Sturteuant</hi> his manner and Inuention.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall bee further mentioned and enlarged in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 6.</hi> Hydrelica.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HYdrelica,</hi> is an Ignick inuention, for the cheaper making of all kindes of hotte liquids, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoures, by the meanes of <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, wherevpon the materials made by this arte are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hydrelicks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18513:29"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>The contents of</hi> Hydrelica <hi>in the ſeuerall Materials which the Arte maketh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Hydre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials are, as
<list>
                        <item>All kinde of <hi>Hydre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> waters and their concreats, of which there are diuerſe ſorts, as
<list>
                              <item>1. All bathing waters, for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the body.</item>
                              <item>2. All kind of waſhing, ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring waters, for waſhing of foule veſſels, foule linen and other cloth.</item>
                              <item>3. All kinde of hot-borne, or liquor, for making of beare or ale, or any other kind of Beauoridge.</item>
                              <item>4. All kinde of hot or warme waters for dying of cloth, ſilke, or leathers, &amp;c.</item>
                              <item>5. All kind of hot-waters for Felt-making.</item>
                              <item>6. Laſtly, all hot-waters for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trades, occupations or myſteries, as the Treatiſe further expreſſeth.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. Al kind of <hi>Hydre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> vnctions, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids, or liquours, which flame or burne, and their concreats, as
<list>
                              <item>1. Oyles, Tallowes, Fatts, Marrowes, and ſuch like.</item>
                              <item>2. Waxes, Roſſens, Pitches, Tarres, Turpentines, brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, &amp; ſuch like vnctions, gummes.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18513:30"/>
                        <item>3. Al kind of <hi>Hydre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> liquors which are mixed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and vnctious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids &amp; their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creats, as.
<list>
                              <item>1. All kind of Sopes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they bee black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopes, ſweet-ſopes, or white-ſopes.</item>
                              <item>2. Any other compound <hi>Hydrelick,</hi> which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after may bee deuiſed or found out, by the ſaid <hi>S. Sturteuant</hi> his inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo ſorth, as it ſhall bee further mentioned and enlarged in the printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 7.</hi> Hydrometallica.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HYdrometallica</hi> is an Ignick inuention, which with the ſame furnace, maketh at the ſame time, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talique Materials, and Hydrelick Materials, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by meanes of <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Materials, made and brought forth by this Art, are procreated as pares, twins and couples, and are called from hence <hi>Hydrometalicks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The contents of</hi> Hydrometallica, <hi>beeing an Inuention compounded of two kinds, is diuerſe and manifold, according to the ſeuerall coupling and ioyning of the oppoſite ſimples together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18513:30"/>
                  <p> As for example
<list>
                        <item>2. Mettle-ſtones prepared and hot-waters.</item>
                        <item>1. Irons and hot-waters.</item>
                        <item>3. Leads and hot-waters.</item>
                        <item>4. Tins and hot-waters.</item>
                        <item>5. Glaſſe-mettle &amp; hot-waters, and ſo other couples of oppoſite <hi>Metaliques</hi> and <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drelicks.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall be further mentioned, and enlarged in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 8.</hi> Hydropreſſoria.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HYdropreſsoria,</hi> is an Ignick inuention, which with the ſame fire, and the ſame furnace, maketh at the ſame time Preſ-wares &amp; <hi>Hydrelick</hi> Materials both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by the meanes of the <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, wherevpon the Materials made and brought forth by this Art, are procreated, as pares, twins, or couples, and are called from hence <hi>Hydro preſſwares.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The contents of</hi> Hydropreſſoria, <hi>beeing an Inuention compounded of two kinds, is diuers and manifold, according to the ſeuerall coupling and ioyning of the oppoſite ſimples together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for example.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Preſt-pipes and hot-waters.</item>
                     <item>2. Preſt-tiles and hot-waters.</item>
                     <item>3. Preſt-bricks and hot-waters.</item>
                     <item>4. Preſt-monions and hot-waters.</item>
                     <item>5. And ſuch like combination &amp; couples.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall be further mentioned and enlarged in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18513:31"/>
                  <head>SECT. 9. <hi>Hydroterrica.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HYdroterrica</hi> is an Ignicke inuention, which with the ſame fire, and the ſame furnace, maketh at the ſame time, <hi>Terricke</hi> materials, and <hi>Hydrelicke</hi> materials both together, by meanes of metallicall inſtruments, whereupon the materials made, and brought forth by this art, are procreated as pares, twins, or couples, and are called from hence <hi>Hydroterrickes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The contents of Hydroterrica, being an Inuention compounded of two kinds, is diuers and manifold, according to the ſeueral coupling, and ioyning of the oppoſite ſimples together, as.</p>
                  <p>Burnt-earth, and hot-water.</p>
                  <list>
                     <label>As for Example.</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Bricks, and hot-water.</item>
                           <item>2. Tiles, and hot-water.</item>
                           <item>3. Potter-ware, and hot-water.</item>
                           <item>4. And ſuch like combination, &amp; couples.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall be further mentioned and enlarged in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note alſo that the compound arts, being rightly and diſcreetely performed, are farre more profitable,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18513:31"/>then the practiſe of the ſingle arts alone, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe that by ſuch a compound furnace, two different workes are done at once, and in a manner with the ſame charge.</p>
                  <p>And theſe are the ſeuen ſeuerall heads, and kindes of inuentions: The generall whereof is called <hi>Ignime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are alſo diuers other new Arts, and inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which worke not with fire, al which ariſe (in reſpect of the meanes and inſtruments) from the former, And therefore, the generall of them all, is called <hi>Ignime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica,</hi> or <hi>Metall-organica,</hi> as was ſpecified before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. 10.</hi> Metall-organica.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MEtall-organica</hi> is an inuention Ignicke, for the cheaper making, &amp; acquiring of diuerſe profitable things, workes, and materials, by the meanes of the <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, fire onely excepted, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the things made and acquired by this art, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Metall-organickes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Metall-organica,</hi> comprehendeth many worthie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, whereof theſe ſeuen are principall, euery one of them making royalties a peece, excepting the wood pleite art.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, then there is a new art and inuention, <hi>Metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorganicke,</hi> with cheifely, by meanes of <hi>Plegnicke</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, maketh a new kinde of water-milnes, wind-milnes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18513:32"/>and winde water milnes, and a new kinde of horſe-milnes, and hand-milnes, for the grinding of corne, tanners barke, brazill, for the ſawing of woods, making of oiles, battering of Irons and coppers, and for tuckeage, and fulleage of wollen cloath, or yeallow oyled leathers, or for any other vſe or purpoſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, which other milnes are ordinarily turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. And theſe <hi>Metalorganicke</hi> milnes, are leſſe charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make, ſet vp, keepe and repaire, and yet more neceſſarie and conuenient, then the ordinarie ſort of milnes, which be now in vſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, there is another new art and inuention, <hi>Metallorganicke,</hi> which chiefly by meanes of <hi>Plegnicke</hi> inſtruments, maketh alſo an artificiall kind of water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, for the aboundant raiſing and mounting of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, after an eaſier order, then thoſe that are already in vſe in the common wealth.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, there is another new art and inuention <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallorganicke,</hi> which chiefly by meanes of <hi>Plegnicke</hi> &amp; <hi>Lenick</hi> inſtruments, ioyntly together, maketh ſingular, effectuall and moſt excellent deuices. and meanes for the dreyning and drying of marſhes, fennes, and low-grounds.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, there is another new art and inuention <hi>Metallorganicke,</hi> which chiefly by meanes of <hi>Plegnike</hi> and <hi>Lenicke</hi> inſtruments, ioyntly together, maketh ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, effectual &amp; moſt excellent deuiſes &amp; meanes for the ridding, clearing, and mounting of waters out of Colepits &amp; Minerals, the like was neuer in vſe or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize before.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18513:32"/>
                  <p> And here the Ballance engin, made of preſſwares, is of great and worthie good vſe.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, there is another new art and inuention <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talorganicke,</hi> which chiefely by meanes of <hi>Plegnicke, Lenicke,</hi> and <hi>Caminicke</hi> inſtruments, ioyntely together maketh ſingular, effectuall and moſt excellent deuiſes for the firtelizing, hartening, and improuing of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ground, corne ground, and all other barren grounds whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, there is another new art and inuention <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallerganicke,</hi> which chiefely by meanes of the <hi>Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke</hi> inſtuments, maketh very effectuall and benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all inſtruments of fiſhing, as new kinde of Burces, new kinde of Nettage, and Bateage, by which new deuiſed meanes great aboundance of fiſh may be caught with farre leſſe charges, and in ſhorter time, then by the ordinary arts of fiſhing.</p>
                  <p>Seuenthly, there is another new art and inuention, <hi>Metallorganicke,</hi> which chiefly by meanes of the <hi>Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke</hi> inſtruments maketh diuerſe kinds of houſehould moueables, as artificial Dores, Windowes, Curteines, Preſſes, Tables, Stooles, Beadſteds, Hangings, Cheſts, and diuers other things, handſomer &amp; more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent then heretofore is done by the ordinatie way of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtuffe.</p>
                  <p>Where note, that the Materials made by this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicke art, are called wood-pleits.</p>
                  <p>And ſo forth, as it ſhall bee further mentioned and enlarged in the Printed treatiſe of <hi>Metallica.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:18513:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 3.</hi> Heuretica defined and deuided into his reall and Tecknick parts.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR yoù hauing thus ſet downe both the Tranſcript of his Maieſties Indenture and the Schedules anexed, I pray you proceed more fully to entreat of the doctrine of <hi>Metallica,</hi> which ſeemeth to be handled in the next place.</p>
               <p>A. It appeareth out of the firſt Section of the Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules, annexed to the Patent, that the doctrine of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallica</hi> cannot diſtinctly be knowne or Methodically expreſſed, except that the art which preſcribeth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, general to all arts and Inuentions, called <hi>Heure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> be firſt precognized.</p>
               <p>R. 7. Define therefore breefely <hi>Heuretica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Heuretica</hi> is the Art of Inuentions, teaching how to find out new, and to iudge of the old.</p>
               <p>R. 8. What deuiſion is there for <hi>Heuretica?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The doctrine of Inuentions hath two parts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and Technick.</p>
               <p>R. 9. Define the Reall part.</p>
               <p>A. Reall is the firſt Part of <hi>Heuretica,</hi> which treateth of the Inſtruments and Reall things, which belong to the Inuentions.</p>
               <p>R. 10. How is the reall part deuided;</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18513:33"/>
               <p> A. The Reall part ſpreadeth it ſelfe into two bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whereof the firſt is called Organick, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Emporeuticall or Polecall.</p>
               <p>R. 11. Define the Organick part.</p>
               <p>A. The organick is a part of <hi>Heuretica,</hi> which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe the meanes and Inſtruments, whereby the work of Art, intended, is brought forth, made and effected,</p>
               <p>R. 12. Define the Emporeuticall or Poleck part.</p>
               <p>A. The Emporeutick is an Organick part of <hi>Heure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> which treateth of the worke of the art, which are commodities and wares for vſe and ſale, wherby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit is raiſed.</p>
               <p>Where note that the comodities, wares and things of euery inuention, for generall vſe, are called from this part Emporeuticks.</p>
               <p>Note alſo, that Emporeuticks, being things artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, are alſo fitly called materialls, but if they be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, they are called things accquired by the art. So fiſh and foule are the Emporeutick things, acquired by the art of fiſhing and fouling, but lead and Iron are Emporeutick Materials made &amp; wrought by <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallicque</hi> art.</p>
               <p>R. 13. Define the <hi>Technick</hi> part.</p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Technick</hi> is that habituall part of <hi>Heuretica,</hi> which treateth of the dexterous habit and faculty wherewith all the Artizands are to be quallified and endowed, who are apointed to make the Emporeutick workes of Inuentions,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18513:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 4.</hi> Another partition of Heuretica and an Inuention Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick defined.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="14">14 WHat other diuiſion is there for <hi>Heuretica?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Heuretica</hi> in reſpect of the worke inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded is diuided into two parts, namely, into the Scientiffick part and Mechanick part.</p>
               <p>R. 15. Define the Scientiffick part.</p>
               <p>A. The Scientiffick is that part of <hi>Heuretica</hi> which preſcribeth prceepts generall to all liberall arts, the end of which Arts, is cheefely Science or knowledge and not any reall viſible worke, or ſenſible thing.</p>
               <p>R. Define the Mechanick part.</p>
               <p>A. The Mechanick part is that part of <hi>Heuretica</hi> which preſcribeth precepts generall to all illiberall arts, the end of which arts is cheefly a reall viſible work or ſenſible thing.</p>
               <p>And the Inuention in this kind is called an Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Mechanick.</p>
               <p>R. 16. Define therefore an Inuention Mechanick.</p>
               <p>A. A Mechanick Inuention is the art of the Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, which by effectuall Inſtruments and meanes brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth ſome new viſible or ſenſible worke good and profitable to the common-wealth.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:18513:34"/>
               <p> So the Inuention of printing is the ſkill and art of <hi>Fauſtus Guttenbergius,</hi> which miſtery (by the effectual deuiſed means of the Preſſe, the Incke, the Characters and paper) bringeth forth impreſſions and Bookes, which Mechanick workes are profitable and good for mans vſe.</p>
               <p>Where note, that, Firſt the Mechanick Art, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Inſtruments and meanes, thirdly the worke of the art, made by thoſe Inſtruments, and meanes, are all called Mechanicks, and are all Inuentions in reſpect of the Author that deuiſed them.</p>
               <p>R. 17. Expreſſe further euery word and clauſe of this definition, to the intent that I may the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them.</p>
               <p>A. Your deſire ſhall bee ſatiſfied. Firſt then to ſpeake of the thing defined, you muſt note that any other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, courſe or way which bringeth forth no externall or Materiall worke, are alſo in reſpect of the Inuentor tearmed Inuentions.</p>
               <p>So the firſt diſcouery of the weſt Indies by <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> (in reſpect of him) is fitly called his Inuention, and the turning point of Nauigation called the Cape of <hi>bona Sperança</hi> is <hi>Gaymus</hi> his inuention the like may be ſaid of <hi>fretum Magellanicum,</hi> and <hi>fretum Dauies,</hi> which although they are laudable Inuentions, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by ingenious &amp; venturous perſons, yet cannot they be ſaid to be Mecanicks. becauſe they produce or leaue behind them Mechanick work, nor had any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick inſtruments made by hands of man directly,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18513:35"/>and of purpoſe for the performance of them, for theſe Mechanicks are onely propper to theſe kinds of inuentions which wee treate of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 18. Wherefore call you an inuention a Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Arte.</p>
               <p>A. To put a diſtinction betweene theſe inuentions Mechanicall, and other inuentions of the liberall Arts and Sciences, of which ſort are Logick, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Grammer, and the Mathematicall ſciences, all which had their firſt Authours and Inuentors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 19. Wherfore ſay you the art of Inuentioner.</p>
               <p>A. To ſhew that there is no Inuention without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Inuentioner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 20. Why then it ſeemeth that all Arts, ſciences, myſteries, trades, crafts, things and deuiſes, which are now extant in the common-wealth, are, and may bee called Inuentions.</p>
               <p>A. Yea verily ſo they may, if wee reſpect the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentioner, and firſt Authors of them, but if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the perſons that vſe and put in practize the ſaid Inuentions at the ſecond hand, as we ſay, ſuch as are the Artificers, Tradeſmen and others that make the ſaid Mechanick workes, in reſpect of theſe ſecondary perſons they are called Arts, Trades, Crafts, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Miſteries, Occupations, Profeſſions, and ſlightes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So the printing, as alſo the Preſſe, the Paper, the Characters, together with the works done, as impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, bookes, and vollumes, in reſpect of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> are his Inuention, but in reſpect of Printers, which now
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18513:35"/>a dayes worke by his inuention, Printing is rightly called an arte, trade, or miſtery, the like may bee ſaid of all other Mechanicall trades now extant in the common-wealth, and of all other profitable inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which here-after may be brought to light in the common-wealth.</p>
               <p>R. 21. To what vſe ſerueth the knowledge of this.</p>
               <p>A. This fitly ſerueth to refute the erronious folly of ſuch ſhallow ſimple perſons, which cannot abide any new inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which this our age bringeth forth, they vtterly diſtaſte both the proiects and Inuentors, they forſooth (as they ſay) will giue no aſſiſtance, they will not meddle nor deale with them, they will not vſe their new worke, though neuer ſo good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, nay they ſay more, after their fond faſhion, it will neuer prooue good, or come to paſſe, with a hundred ſuch like ſpeeches, tending to the diſpraiſe both of the Inuentioner, and of things deuiſed by him, but being demanded for their reaſon, they haue none to alleadge, except onely a womans reaſon, like vnto that of the Epigrammatiſt:
<q>
                     <l>Non amo te <hi>Voluſi,</hi> non poſſum dicere quare,</l>
                     <l>Hoc tantum poſsum dicere, non amo te.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But if theſe men, who ſo much ſpurne at inuentions, did well conſider, that all ancient Mechanick trades, occupations, profeſſions and workes, which now are in vſe in the common-wealth, were new at the firſt, and had their beginning and infancy, and how they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18513:36"/>were then the peculiar inuentions of ſome ingenious wits, who trauelled with all their endeuours to bring forth the ſaid inuentions, to the good of that age wherein they liued. If I ſay they did well, conſider and ponder this, they would not be ſo auerſe and bitter againſt laudable, and good proiects, brought forth now a dayes, for with as good reaſon they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh againſt printing, ſhipping, milning and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, againſt the ordinary waies of making of ſalts, alloms, coppreſſes, and ſaultpeeter, againſt the trade and art of making of hats, and knit-ſtockings, ſhooes, bootes, and apparell, againſt the art and trade of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſaddles, carts, ploughes, harrowes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the art of melting, founding, and caſting of mettles, of forging, hammering, and battering of irons, braſſe, peuters, ſiluer, and gould; and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt all other trades, occupations, vocations, and profeſſions in the common-wealth, as ſo baſely to regard and eſteeme the proffitable and new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of our daies. Againe, in ſcorning, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of profitable buſineſſe of late inuention, they ſet themſelues not onely againſt man, but alſo againſt the ſpirit of God, who is the authour of the ſaid gifts, and firſt worke of them in man, as it is expreſſely taught in the 31. of <hi>Exodus:</hi> in the example of two worthy inuentioners, and artificers, the wordes of the text are theſe. Behold (ſaith God to <hi>Moſes</hi>) I haue called by name <hi>Bezaleele</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Vri,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hur,</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> whom I haue filled with the ſpirit of God in wiſedome and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18513:36"/>in vnderſtanding, and in knowledge, and in all worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, to finde out curious workes, to worke in gold, in ſiluer, and in braſſe. Alſo the Art to ſet ſtones, and to carue in timber, and to worke in all manner of workemanſhip. And behold I haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him <hi>Aholiab,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ahiſamah</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> and in the hearts of all that are wiſe-harted, I haue put wiſedome to make all that I haue commanded thee.</p>
               <p>Out of which words of holy Scripture it is apparent that all Mechanicke Arts and Inuentions, as well as the graces of ſaluation, are the peculiar workes, and gifts of Gods holy ſpirit in man, which bloweth where, and when he liſteth, and powreth out his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vpon ſome men in euery age.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 5.</hi> Tranſient instrumentall meanes.</head>
               <p>R. 22. In the definition of the Organicke part, you ſay that the worke is produced by inſtruments and meanes, I would therefore know of you, how many kindes of inſtruments and meanes there are to effect a new buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>A. The Organick things for the effecting of a new Inuention are of two ſorts, Permanent or Tranſient.</p>
               <p>R. 23. Deſcribe the Tranſient Inſtrument and meanes.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18513:37"/>
               <p> A Inſtruments and means are ſaid to be Tranſient, when in reſpect of their vſe, they ſerue but once for that imployment for which they were appointed, ſo fuell and oare are Tranſient, becauſe they waſt and conſume in that Materiall which they make.</p>
               <p>R. 24. How many kindes are there of this Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſort</p>
               <p>A. Two: Efficientall, or Materiall.</p>
               <p>R. 25. Deſcribe the Efficientall Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>A. Efficientall are ſuch Tranſient Inſtruments and meanes as vaniſh and conſume away in their firſt vſe, whilſt they are performing their operation and efficiency to produce the pretended Mechanick work, as namely the fuell or fiering in euery buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>R. 26. Deſcribe the Materiall Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>A. Materiall, are ſuch Tranſient Inſtruments and meanes wherof the Inſtruments conſiſt and are made, not vading or vaniſhing away, but remaining tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed or altered in the ſubſtance of the thing ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, as namely the ſtuffe and matter of euery Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick inſtrument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAPVT. 6.</hi> Permanent Inſtruments and meanes.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="27">27. I vnderſtand well the Tranſient inſtruments, with their ſeuerall kindes, pray you deſcribe the permanent.</p>
               <p>A. Inſtruments and meanes are ſaid to be perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent when as they ſerue to performe their operations
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18513:37"/>diuerſe times (to wit) in this thing, in that thing, and in many others, of this ſort are all tooles in euery trade, all kilnes, furnaces, ouens, hearthes, in euery trade. If we reſpect the firſt making and creation of permanent inſtruments, then muſt we conſider their efficientall, and materiall meanes alſo.</p>
               <p>R. 28. How many kindes are their of this ſort.</p>
               <p>A. Two, for theſe permanent meanes, are either perſonall, as namely the workeman and artificers in euery action; or elſe imperſonall, of which ſort are all other inſtruments of the buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>R. 29. How many ſorts of workemen are there for euery inuention.</p>
               <p>A. Two, primary, and annuall, primarie as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentioner to guide, and artificers to make, the annuall are the daily workemen which make the Mechanicke.</p>
               <p>R. 30. How many artificers are neceſſarie for the prymarie, and firſt foundation of mechanicke inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>A. Theſe ſubſequent are moſt neceſſarie, as namely; Ioyners, Carpenters, Smithes, Brickelayers, Maſons, whereunto in ſeuerall inuentions, diuerſe other Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are to be added, as occaſion ſerueth, as Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, Glouers, Bellowes-makers &amp;c.</p>
               <p>R. 31. How many ſorts of annuall workemen are neceſſarie for the yearely managing of an inuention.</p>
               <p>A. Two, the maiſter and ouerſeer, or his appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, or ſeruants, which make the mechanicke worke, And ſecondly, the repairationers, which maintaine and mend the inſtruments and meanes which at the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18513:38"/>firſt they made and formed.</p>
               <p>R. 32. What diſtribution haue you for imperſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall inſtruments.</p>
               <p>A. The imperſonall inſtruments, are either gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſpeciall, the generall is the worke-houſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in other inſtruments doe their operations, worke and imployment, and vnder this head we comprehend the ground, place, yard, or roome, where the <hi>Mechanicke</hi> buſineſſe is wrought or done. The ſpeciall imperſonall inſtruments, are all other imperſonall inſtruments, beſides the worke-houſe or place. Amongſt which imperſonall inſtruments furnacing may here bee briefely touched as being a neceſſarie inſtrument in moſt inuentions.</p>
               <p>R. 33. How define you a furnace.</p>
               <p>A. A furnace is the artificiall receptacle, which beareth and conteineth fewell and the fire.</p>
               <p>R. 34. How may kindes are comprehended vnder this head of furnacing.</p>
               <p>A. Diuerſe, as namely all kinde of ouens, lamps, ſtoues, kilnes, hearths, all which we generally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend vnder the name of Furnacing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 7.</hi> Inſtruments and meanes procured and meerely opperatiue, monies and charges of a buſineſse.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="35">35. WHat other diſtribution haue you of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and meanes of a buſines, in reſpect of charges.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:18513:38"/>
               <p> A. Organicke meanes of a Mechanicke, are either procuring, or meerely opperatiue.</p>
               <p>The procuring meanes is monie to be impended and disburſed in charges.</p>
               <p>It is the inſtrument of inſtruments, and meane of meanes, procuring all other inſtruments and meanes meerely opperatiue, and when once they are procured and prouided by it, it meaſureth their worth and val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation, whereupon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth it, <hi>communis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura omnium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>R. 36. What is generally to be knowne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, concerning the monies to be disburſed in a buſines.</p>
               <p>A. Monies or charges of a buſines, are either pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie and once impended, or elſe annuall, and at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine times to be renewed.</p>
               <p>R. 37. What differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces are their of primary monies.</p>
               <p>A. Primary monies are either disburſements about the firſt foundation, or about the tryall.</p>
               <p>R. 38. What call you fundamentall charges.</p>
               <p>A. Charges of foundation are all ſuch primary monies which are to be disburſed at the firſt erection or ſetting vp of a new buſineſſe, or of grand Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes, in ſome one conuenient place, whereby a worke-houſe is furniſhed with all permanent neceſſary tooles and inſtruments.</p>
               <p>R. What call you charges of tryall.</p>
               <p>A. Charges of tryall are the primary monies which are beſtowed and disburſed about the tryall and experimenting of an inuention or new buſineſſe.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:18513:39"/>
               <p> R. 40. Wherein conſiſteth the chiefe charges of tryall.</p>
               <p>A. The triall monies are to be disburſed firſt about the Theoricke inſtruments, and meanes of an inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is the whole deſcription of an inuention. Whether it be by way of manuſcript writings, or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted treatiſes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, about the moddles of an inuention, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be ſuperficiall, or reall, motionall or directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall.</p>
               <p>And laſtly about the erection and foundation of the Protoplaſt, vnto which al the other grand mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes are to be conformed.</p>
               <p>R. 41. Concerning the charge of tryall, what is fitteſt for an Inuentioner to demaund of them that are willing to deale in a new buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>It is the wiſeſt, ſafeſt, and moſt credible courſe for the Inuentioner, not to aske vnder-hand, whereby he ſhall be driuen to repaire to them againe the ſecond time, but rather at the firſt let him aske and agree for more monie, and not for leſſe then will ſerue the turne.</p>
               <p>R. 42. What other chiefe rules ought an Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner carefully to obſerue in the practiſe and tryall of any new inuention.</p>
               <p>A. That he may make tryall and put in practiſe his new deuiſe and inuention with good ſucceſſe and to purpoſe, let him alwaies well remember theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent rules.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Make things ſtronger, then that exact ſtrength
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18513:39"/>which the thing is to haue.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Make things greater then that exact greatneſſe which the thing is to haue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And therefore make thinges longer, broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thicker and wider, then that exact length, breadth, thickneſſe and wideneſſe that the thing is to haue.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Make more in number then that exact number which is required to ſerue the turne.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Take longer time for a new buſines then will ſerue the turne.</p>
               <p n="6">6 For quallities as hardnes, ſoftnes, drineſſe, moiſtnes, ſtiffnes, toughnes, &amp;c. obſerue this Rule.</p>
               <p>Let things be tempered to a greater quallity then will ſerue the turne.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Yet if the Inuentioner can make the thing in the exact truth, then let him do it accordingly, for this is alwaies leaſt chargeable.</p>
               <p>R. 43. In the firſt triall of things can the Inuentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner perfectly hit on the exactneſſe of euery particular inſtrument and means belonging to the new buſines.</p>
               <p>A. The Vndertakers and dealers are to expect ſome loſſe in triall of new buſineſſes, be the Inuentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner neuer ſo perfect in his Theorick; for although he do his beſt indeauor, and giue perfect directions to his workmen and Artificers, yet they will often faile and erre in their worke, by which meanes the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being experimented and put to triall, becometh
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18513:40"/>inſufficient, for the appointed vſe, and many times the Inuentioner in ſome one point may faile himſelfe; for which there is no helpe but only to redreſſe and amend the fault in the inſtrument, or elſe to make a new inſtrument in the others ſtead, neither of which can be done but with further charge.</p>
               <p>R. 44. What call you the Annuall charges of an inuention.</p>
               <p>A. Annuall, are ſuch monyes which from time to time, vpon occaſion, are beſtowed after the firſt Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vppon the repairing, maintaining, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the ſaid primary inſtruments belonging to the ſaid new buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAPVT. 8.</hi> Inuentions intermixtand pure moddle, Protoplaſt and grand Mechanick defined.</head>
               <p>YOu haue handled the doctrine of the generall meanes and Inſtruments of Inuentions, proceed I pray you to ſpeake of the differences and diuers kindes of Inuentions, and Firſt therefore I deſire to know.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18513:40"/>
               <p> R. 45. How many ſorts or kindes of Inuention are there being compared or conſidered one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other?</p>
               <p>A. Two, An Inuention is either pure or intermixt, an Inuention is ſaid to bee pure and entire within it ſelfe, when as none of the parts eſſentiall are common to any other Inuention for the ſame vſe.</p>
               <p>Intermixt when as ſome of the parts are found in ſome other former inuention.</p>
               <p>So a Windmill is an intermixt Inuention, becauſe ſome of the partes, as namely the Milne ſtones, the rong-wheeles and the Cogg-wheeles were firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in awater-milne or horſe-milne and quernes.</p>
               <p>But a hand-Querne was a pure and ſimple Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on becauſe none of the parts there of were formerly extant in any other Mechanick.</p>
               <p>And ſo printing is a pure and ſimple Inuention, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none of the eſſentiall parts thereof were taken from any former Inuention, where they were appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſame vſe.</p>
               <p>Where note that the common parts of an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt Inuention are to be eſteemed as propper and peculiar to the ſame Inuention, when as they are conioyned and mixed in with other new things Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and meanes, which are the eſſentiall parts of the new deuiſe.</p>
               <p>R. 46. What other diſtribution haue you of an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uention in reſpect of magnitude.</p>
               <p>A. In reſpect of greatneſſe or quantity, there are
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18513:41"/>three ſorts of inuentions, namely the Moddle, the Protoplaſt, and the grand Mechanick.</p>
               <p>R. 47. Deſcribe the Moddle.</p>
               <p>A. The Moddle is a Mechanick, which onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth and decyphereth, in ſome little platforme, the true part and lineaments of the Mechanick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, beeing inſufficient to yeeld any Emporeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick vſe of the inuention.</p>
               <p>So the Moddle of a winde-milne, repreſenteth the failes and other parts of Fabrick and ſtructure, but grindeth no corne.</p>
               <p>Where note, that ſome times the moddle is to be made greater then the Mechanick, eſp ecially in ſmall curious things, as in a watch, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>R. 48. How many ſorts of moddles are there.</p>
               <p>A. Two, Superficiall and Reall.</p>
               <p>The Superficiall deſcribeth onely the parts and line aments in paper, bordes or paſt-bords, by lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, drawing, or painting, ſhewing no action or opperation, nor corporall dimenſions of the parts.</p>
               <p>A Reall moddle is that which ſheweth euery part of the greater Mechanick, in a true and liuely (though little) proportion, hauing his parts fitted for motion, action, or opperation: Neuertheleſſe it is not ſo effectuall or fully vſe-full, beeing onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatiue, as was touched before.</p>
               <p>So a little ſhip, which you haue hanging vp in a marchants houſe, is the Reall moddle of a grand ſhip or ſea veſſell, becauſe it repreſenteth euery part and action thereof.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:18513:41"/>
               <p> R. 49. What is the principall vſe of a Reall Mod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</p>
               <p>A. The cheefeſt vſe of a reall moddle is that the Inuention may thereby more perfectly and exactly direct both himſelfe, and alſo guide his workmen for the finiſhing of any grander Mechanick of the ſame kind, thereby the better to produce and bring forth the Theorick conceiued in his mind into the grand Reall Inuention.</p>
               <p>So the vſe of a ſmall reall moddle of a Wind-milne ſerueth uery fitly to direct both the Inuentor himſelfe and likewiſe all his Carpenters and other workmen, to proceed infallibly to build and ſet vp a reall and grand windmilne intended to be made.</p>
               <p>R. 50. How many ſorts of reall moddles are there.</p>
               <p>A. There are two ſorts, for either they are meerely directionall or alſo motionall.</p>
               <p>Directionall is that moddle which is made only to direct and guide the Artificer in the dimenſions of all the parts, as alſo for to direct them for the kinds of the matter and the ſtuffe that they are to haue to make the engin intended.</p>
               <p>R. 51. What is the fitteſt and cheapeſt ſtuffe to make a directionall moddle of.</p>
               <p>A. Paſt-boordes and reedes are the fitteſt either for Iron-works or woodworks, wherof the Paſt-bords are in ſtead of boordes, plancks and bed-ſides.</p>
               <p>And the Reeds are to repreſent round Cylindriack timber, as alſo other ſquare timber, as namely ſingle
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18513:42"/>quarters, double quarters, puncheons, rafters, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummes &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So that of theſe the Inuentioner may fitly and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily make and contriue the fabricke and ſtructure of any directionall moddle.</p>
               <p>R. 52. What call you a motionall moddle.</p>
               <p>A. A motionall is that moddle Reall which is made compleat in euery part, hauing his true vſe, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration and motion, as in the grander <hi>Mechanickes,</hi> yet hauing no Emporeuticke commodity, but onely for ſhew and tryall, and not for ſale and vſe.</p>
               <p>There are three degrees in this motionall moddle, the meane moddle, the leſſer then the meane, the greater then the meane.</p>
               <p>The meane moddle is a motionall, which hath his magnitude and greatneſſe betweene the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, being the leaſt chargeable to be made. And it is alwaies greater then the leſſer motionall, and leſſer then the greater motion all: and there is but one meane modle to be found in the progreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame degres</p>
               <p>Where note that it belongeth principally to the Inuentioners skil and care to ſet forth the dimenſions and parts of his moddle, intended with the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of charges that may be, and in the eaſieſt and redieſt manner for his workemen to vnderſtand and imitate, or elſe he hitteth not vpon the meane mod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, but vpon ſome other extreame.</p>
               <p>R. 53. Define the Protoplaſt.</p>
               <p>A. The Protoplaſt is an Inuention mechanick which firſt is ſet vp of that kind, and ſeruing to profitable
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18513:42"/>Emporeuticke vſes, hauing all the principall parts, actions, and perfections, which all other ſubſequent grand Mechanicks ought to haue of the ſame kinde, which afterward are to be made and framed by it.</p>
               <p>So the firſt windmilne that the inuentioner euer ſet vp to grinde corne was the Protoplaſt and example from whence all other wind-milnes ſprange and were deriued, the like may bee ſaid of the firſt of euery kinde of Mechanicke, as of <hi>Faustus</hi> his firſt Printing Preſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>R. 54. Define a grand Mechanicke.</p>
               <p>A. The grand Mechanicke, is that which is ſet vp after the forme and tipe of his Protoplaſt, for the ſame vſe and purpoſe, onely differing from the Protoplaſt in greatneſſe, or with ſome profitable additions which later experience hath taught.</p>
               <p>So the Windmilnes in More-fields are Mechanicks of that kinde of inuention, for they are builded after the Archerype of the Protoplaſt which the inuentor firſt inuented and erected, ſeruing to the ſame vſe of grinding of corne; they differ onely in this, they haue a deuiſe called the Crampe, which will ſodenly ſtay (in the face of the ſtorme) the violent motion or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumgyration of the wheeles, vntill the ſales are taken downe or fardled vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:18513:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 9.</hi> Innentions <hi>Heterocreſious</hi> and <hi>Homocreſious,</hi> primatiue, and deriuatiue, defined.</head>
               <p>Reader.</p>
               <p n="55">55. VVHat other diſtribution haue you of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick inuention, conſidered one with an other.</p>
               <p>A. Inuentions conſidered compaſatiuely one with another, haue two differences, for they are eyther <hi>Heterocreſious,</hi> or elſe <hi>Homocreſious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heterocreſious,</hi> are inuentions which produce diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Mechanick workes, wares and commodities. So milning and ſhipping are two <hi>Heterocreſious</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, becauſe the worke of the one is meale or flower, and the worke of the other is carriage or tranſportage.</p>
               <p>R. 56. Define <hi>Homocreſious</hi> Inuentions.</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Homocreſious</hi> inuentions, are ſuch which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and bring forth Emporeuticall workes for the ſame vſe.</p>
               <p>So a horſe-milne, a water milne, a wind-milne are <hi>Homocreſious,</hi> becauſe they all grinde flower, though after different manner and wayes.</p>
               <p>R. 57. What diſtribution haue you for <hi>Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. An Inuention <hi>Homocreſious,</hi> is either primatiue or deriuatiue, the primatiue is that which was the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18513:43"/>firſt in vſe in the world of the ſame kinde.</p>
               <p>So a Peſtle and a Morter is a primatiue inuention, becauſe it was firſt vſed for to beat and bruſe corne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to meale and powder, and at this day it is ſtill vſed to grinde eaten grotes, but a hand-querne, a horſ-milne, a winde-milne, and a water-milne, are Inuentions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuatiue, all which were found out in ſucceſſion of time, long after the peſtle and the mortar.</p>
               <p>R. 58. Giue ſome other illuſtrious examples of primatiue and deriuatiue inuentions.</p>
               <p>A. In matters of literature, the Art of writing with the pen, is a worthy primatiue inuention, both for writing and reading, found out by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that learned Leuite and thrice holy Prophet, the deriuatiue inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereof is Printing, a far more exquiſite miſtery deuiſed of late yeares by <hi>Fauſtus Guttenbergius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So in husbandry the Spade, the Rake, and Shouell, was a worthy primatiue inuention of <hi>Adam,</hi> for the tillage and ſowing of the ground, according to that ancient and old prouerbe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>When <hi>Adam</hi> digged, and <hi>Eue</hi> ſpan,</l>
                  <l>Who was then a Gentleman.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But the Plough and the Harrow are their deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue inuentions, which for the vſes of husbandry doe farre exceed them, for by them more worke of tillage of the ground may be done in one day with the ſame charge, then could be done by their primatiue inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in twenty dayes.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:18513:44"/>
               <p> Againe the Barrow which carrieth burdens from places is a primatiue inuention, but the Cart with wheeles is a far more excellent deriued Mechanick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it carrieth more in one day, then the primatiue can doe in ten dayes with the ſame charges.</p>
               <p>And this Inuention of round wheeles to draw and carry loades with a ſmall ſtrength vndoubtedly was grounded on this Geometricall <hi>axiom, Circulus tangit planum vnico puncto,</hi> for if the wheeles ſhould haue beene made ſquare, trencher wiſe, or in any other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-angle, forty horſes would not ſo eaſily draw them beeing laden, as two doth now with both ſpeed and eaſe. And thus much for the example of primatiue and deriuatiue Inuentions.</p>
               <p>Where note, that the deriuatiue muſt alwayes bee of a greater vſe, and doe more good in the common wealth, then the primatiue, or elſe it is not to bee receiued.</p>
               <p>Note alſo, if there be many deriuatiues in the ſame kinde, the latter inuention muſt alwayes better the former, and beeing all of them compared and ranck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their primatiue, they make an Inuentionall progreſſion, one exceeding an other, in goodneſſe and vſe, amongſt which, the laſt of all ought to bee the beſt, and is therefore called the Eumechanick in the progreſſion of that kinde.</p>
               <p>R. 59. Giue ſome examples of Inuentionall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</p>
               <p>A. I will ſatisfie your deſire, and firſt in matter of husbandry, for the making of bread, which maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18513:44"/>the life of man, there is a progreſſion of theſe fiue Inuentions.</p>
               <p>Firſt the Mortar, ſecondly the Hand-querne, thirdly the Horſe-milne, fourthly the Water-milne, fiftly the Winde-milne.</p>
               <p>To which if we adde the inuention of the Plegnick Milne, it maketh vp the ſixt, and is the Eumechanick of that kinde.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in hoſe or ſtockings, there is a progreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of three, cloth or kerſey ſtockings, which were firſt in vſe: Secondly in knit ſtockings with Needles: Thirdly, and laſtly, in knit ſtockings with loome, which is a late Inuention of one Maiſter <hi>Lee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in veſſels of drinking, there is a large progreſſion. For firſt, to pretermit the cup of the hand, out of which <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Gedeons</hi> three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Souldiers dranke, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.6. There is ſecondly the earthen Pitcher, which the Samaritane woman had at the Well: and the third roome came vp the vſe of the black Leather Iacks, an ancient drinking veſſell of our natiue countrymen, and the fourth place ſprung vp the vſe of Tankards and Wodden Kans, in the fift out of Hornes, in the ſixt Silues, Gould, greene-Glaſſe, Venice glaſſe, and Peuter.</p>
               <p>All inuentions, for the moſt part, of latter times, are deriuatiue, &amp; the Inuentioners are to make choice of this kinde, and needeth the leſſe to ſpend his time about any primatiue deuice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18513:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 10.</hi> Inuentions organicall and emporeuticall: The parts and adiuncts: The Theoricke and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke of an Inuention Organicall.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="60">60. VVhat other diſtribution is their of an inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mechanicke.</p>
               <p>A. An inuention Mechanicke, in reſpect of vſe is either <hi>Organicall</hi> or <hi>Emporeuticall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Inuention <hi>Organicall</hi> is that artificiall fabricke or ſtructure compacted of all imperſonall inſtruments and meanes which make the Emporeuticke comodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>So the windmilne conſidered in it ſelfe is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, ſtructure or fabricke, which comprehendeth all permanent inſtruments and meanes which produce, yeeld, and bring forth meale or flower.</p>
               <p>But the flower and meale thus ground and made by the windemilne <hi>Engin</hi> is fitly called the inuention emporeuticall.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the whole ſtructure and complement of all the permanent, and imperſonall inſtruments, and meanes which make vp the Ferricall furnace, is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the inuention.</p>
               <p>R. 61. What differences haue you for the parts of an Inuention <hi>Organicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The parts of an inuention <hi>Organicall,</hi> are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſſentiall or ineſſentiall, comon or peculiar <hi>Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18513:45"/>
               <p> But the earth-coale iron which is made by the ſaid complement, and panoply of inſtruments is fitly called the Emporeuticall inuention of the Author or Inuentor.</p>
               <p>R. 62. Deſcribe the eſſentiall parts of an inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Organicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The eſſentiall part of an inuention <hi>Organicall</hi> is any maine and chiefe member, whereby the engin is well enabled to performe his worke and operation, which being lacking, the other parts of the engin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ineffectuall, and inoperatiue, for the producing the <hi>Emporeuticke</hi> intended.</p>
               <p>So a windmilne conſiſteth of all hiseſſential parts, beſides his croſſe ſales is ineffectuall and not able to grinde corne, the like may be ſaid if it lacke a cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wheele, a ronge wheele, a milne-ſtone, or any other eſſentiall part.</p>
               <p>R. 63. Deſcribe an ineſſentiall part of an Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Organicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. An ineſſentiall part is an additament, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſomewhat bettereth and helpeth the Inuention, when it is added to the maine complement of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> or <hi>Engin,</hi> yet being lacking and not vſed, it taketh not away the opperation or worke of the inuention or engin: of this ſort, is the crampe of a windmilne, which is a very good and worthy addittament, found out by ſome ingenious Milner of late, and it is able to hold the croſſe ſales immoueable, euen in the very blaſt of a ſtorme.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:18513:46"/>
               <p> Yet wind-milnes which haue not nor had not this later addition of the crampe doe daily grinde corne aſwell as other wind-milnes which are there withall furniſhed.</p>
               <p>But in a ſtorme they are driuen to this inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: that three or foure muſt preſently goe downe to turne their croſſe failes out of the winde, that they may take downe and fardle vp their ſailes.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the braſſe plate and the rouling girth are neceſſarie and conuenient additions in the engin of the Printing Preſſe, and both of them were of late yeares firſt deuiſed (as it is ſaid) by one Maiſter <hi>Haruie</hi> an ingenious Printer in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
               <p>Yet before they were added or vſed in the miſtery of Printing, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his inuention was abſolute and compleate of it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>R. 64 Deſcribe the common parts of an inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Organicall.</p>
               <p>The common parts are ſuch as are borrowed from other trades, occupations and miſteries formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented and in vſe, and now adioyned and mixed in, amongſt the new parts of the Inuention.</p>
               <p>R. 65. What call you the peculiar parts of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention.</p>
               <p>A. The peculiar parts are ſuch as are proper and of the eſſence of the inuention, not being taken from any other Mechanicke, formerly in vſe.</p>
               <p>So the ſayles, the milne-poſt, the ſpurs of a wind-milne are his peculiar parts, but the cogge-wheeles,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18513:46"/>ronge-wheeles, and milneſtones are common parts as being aſſumed and borrowed from the horſe-milne and water-milne formerly in vſe.</p>
               <p>R. 66. What differences haue you for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts of an inuention Organicall.</p>
               <p>A. The adiuncts of an inuention Organicall haue the ſame differences, which the parts of an inuention had before.</p>
               <p>For the adiuncts are either eſſentiall or ineſſentiall, common or peculiar, the nature and diſtinction of which differences may be eaſily conceiued and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the deſcriptions of the former ſeuerall parts.</p>
               <p>R. 67. What other differences haue you for the adiuncts of an inuention Organicall.</p>
               <p>A. The adiuncts of an inuention Organicall are alſo neceſſarie or leſſe neceſſarie.</p>
               <p>Neceſſarie adiuncts are all ſuch which of neceſſitie are to be vſed for the producing of the intended Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicke.</p>
               <p>And the leſſe neceſſarie are all ſuch which bringes ſome ſmall helpe to make and bringe forth the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreuticke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>R. 68. What diſtribution haue you of an inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Organicall.</p>
               <p>A. An inuention is ſaid to haue a Theoricke or a Practicke.</p>
               <p>R. 69. What call you Theoricke Inuention.</p>
               <p>A. The Theoricke of an inuention is the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the contents thereof by a plaine and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar diſcription, and that either by manuſcript
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18513:47"/>writings or by printed treatiſes.</p>
               <p>R. 70. What Arguments are cheefe for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of an Inuention.</p>
               <p>A. The arguments of the parts and adiuncts, or the Arguments of Inſtruments and meanes.</p>
               <p>R. 71. Do the parts, and adiuncts, and Inſtruments, and meanes, expreſſe diuers meanes.</p>
               <p>A. No, for by parts and adiuncts are vnderſtood the ſelfe ſame things, which are meant by inſtruments and meanes, but yet in diuers and different reſpects: for they are called parts and adiuncts in reſpect that the Mechanick Engin ſubſiſteth &amp; conſiſteth of them, but in reſpect of the Emporeutick, which is made by them, the ſaid partes and adiuncts are fitly called In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and meanes.</p>
               <p>So a printing Preſſe hath his ſeuerall parts, whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it doth conſiſt, as the ſcrew, the nut, the pare-tree and the chaſe, &amp;c. it hath alſo his adiuncts belonging to it, as the Inck and the Inck-bals &amp;c. which ſaid parts and adiuncts of the Preſſe conſidered, with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted papers, bookes and impreſſions which are the ſale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Emporeutick workes. I ſay in this reſpect they are called Inſtruments and meanes whereby printed Bookes are atteined vnto.</p>
               <p>R 72. Define a practick of an Inuention.</p>
               <p>A The practick of an Inuention is that which is made in reall parts and adiunct, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Theorick of an inuention.</p>
               <p>So if you deſcribe an Iron furnace by euery part and adiunct which belongeth therunto, ſuch a diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18513:47"/>is called the Theorick of a Furnace, but afterward if you make a real Furnace, either of moddle, ſtuffe or of brick, clay, or earth, according to the deſcription &amp; Theorick proportions, then ſuch a Furnace is called the practick of a Furnace, the like may be ſaid of any other Mechanick or Engin.</p>
               <p>R. 73. What cannons haue you of an inuention in reſpect of the Theorick.</p>
               <p>A. The Theorick of an Inuention is to be deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by his parts and adiuncts that other mens labours and indeauors bee incroached vppon or foreſtalled thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 11.</hi> An Inuention triable and vntriable conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inconformable, Royall and Coppy-hold.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="74">74 WHat other kindes or ſorts haue you of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention.</p>
               <p>A. An Inuention is two fould, An Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of diſcouery, or an inuention of experiment, or an Inuention is triable, or vntriable.</p>
               <p>R. 75. What call you a triable Inuention.</p>
               <p>A. A triable Iuuention is an inuention whoſe worth and goodneſſe cannot certainly appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore trialls and experiments be made, not only in the moddles thereof, but alſo in the Protop laſt it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Of this ſort, are all the Inuentions <hi>Metallicall,</hi> compriſed in the Patent and alſo the Inuention called the Regiſter for generall commerce.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:18513:48"/>
               <p> R. 76. Define an inuention vntriable.</p>
               <p>A. An vntryable inuention is a new proiect or diſcouery, whoſe worth and goodneſſe requireth no tryals, but may bee iudged and diſcerned onely by the diſcription or declaration of the plot and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
               <p>Of this ſort are all Monopolies, new cuſtomes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts, taxations, ſubſidies, ſtatutes, with fines, and diuers other ſtate buſineſſes, diſcoueries and inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are ordinarily propounded or petitioned of his Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Of this ſort is Sepherica, a late inuention of the Authours, the proiect and contents whereof ſhall be handled in a treatiſe called <hi>Sepherica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>R. 77. How many ſorts of tryable inuentions are there.</p>
               <p>A. An inuention tryable is either conformeable or inconformeable.</p>
               <p>R. 78. Define a conformeable inuention.</p>
               <p>A. A conformeable inuention is an inuention try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able which reformeth and bettereth a former inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (requiring but ſome ſmall and not chargeable alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) after that the new is vnited to the ould.</p>
               <p>So the Iron furnaces, fineries and chafferies may be much reformed and bettered with ſmall charges, hauing our Ferricall inuention vnited to them, and therefore the Ferricall inuention is fitly called a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeable inuention.</p>
               <p>R. 79. What Cannons or rules haue you for a conformeable inuention.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:18513:48"/>
               <p> A. Conformeable inuention being priueledged is farre more beneficiall and commodious to the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees &amp; the dealers in that buſines, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an inconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable inuention, and the reaſon is becauſe that ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the grand tryals are brought to paſſe and performed in the Protoplaſt, they may chooſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will be at any further charge, and yet they may raiſe preſent rent and benefit by conforming of the former inuentions to the Protoplaſt, and not at theirs, but onely at the charges of the owners of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer works and inuentions.</p>
               <p>R. 80. Define an inconformable inuention.</p>
               <p>A. An inuention is ſaid to be inconformable whoſe Protoplaſt being erected and ſet vp, cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to any former inuention in vſe, where by yearely profits of conformity may be raiſed without charges to the Pattentees and dealers.</p>
               <p>So the preſſeware inuention maketh tiles and brickes, and all other clayworks, after a farre more gainefull and beneficiall manner then by the ordinary courſe, yet neuertheleſſe it is an inconformable inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe that the ordinary Arts of tilemaking and brick-making cannot bee conformed vnto the Preſſe-ware Protoplaſt with ſome ſmall alterations and ſmall charges.</p>
               <p>R. 81. What Cannons or Rules haue you of an inconformable inuention.</p>
               <p>A. An inconformable inuention requireth a great ſtocke and great disburſements for the Pattentees,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18513:49"/>to lay out, aſwell for the Protapleſt as alſo for ſome two or three grander Mechanicks thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly an inconformable inuention after the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and perfection of the Protoplaſt in continew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time, may raiſe great rents and fines by licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leaſes and deuiſes though no by preſent confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
               <p>R. 82. What other diſtribution haue you for an inuention Mechanicke.</p>
               <p>A. An inuention Mechanicke, is either priuiledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or vnpriuiledged, againe it is either a royaltie or a coppy-hould.</p>
               <p>A royaltie is ſuch a new buſineſſe, which in regard of the greatneſſe thereof belongeth peculiarly to the King.</p>
               <p>Or a royaltie is an inuention Mechanicke which produceth extraordinarie and worthie yearely profits and reuenewes, whoſe valuation exceedeth the ſumme of ten thouſand pounds. <hi>per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>R. 83. Define a coppy-hould inuention.</p>
               <p>A. A Coppy-hould is an inuention whoſe yearely valuation and worth exceedeth not the ſumme of ten thouſand pounds. <hi>per annum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="84">84. What cannons or rules haue you concerning royall or coppy-hould Inuentions.</p>
               <p>A. Theſe Cannons belong to a Royall Inuention, firſt, no ſubiect or ſubiects, of what eſtate or degree ſoeuer by his ſeruice or demerit, except the Queene mother, the Kings children, is capeable of a whole en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire royaltie, and therefore if the King haue paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18513:49"/>way a royaltie, ignorantly, he may iuſtly recall and reuoke his graunt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a ſubiect may by his ſeruice to his Prince and Country, demerit part or portion of a royaltie, it being no greater then a Coppy-hould.</p>
               <p>R. 85. What Cannons or Rules belong to a Mechanicke in reſpect of priuiledge or impriueledge.</p>
               <p>A. Firſt, it is moſt reaſonable and fitting that a Mechanicke inuention ſhould be priueledged for a certaine time wholly to the Inuentioner &amp; Authour, if ſo be it be but of the yearely valew of a Coppy-hould.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the firſt Inuentor of a Royaltie though of meane degree hath as great demerit in the inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as any other ſubiect of what eſtate or degree ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, excepting Royall perſons.</p>
               <p>R. 86. What Cannons or rules haue you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Royalties.</p>
               <p>A. There are diuers other rules and obſeruations which I ſpare to ſpeake of at this time, becauſe at fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaſure I purpoſe to Print a little Tractate of Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties and coppy-houlds, which is a parcel of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of <hi>Metallita.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 12.</hi> Cannons or rules ſeruing to iudge of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a deriuatine Inuention Emporeuticall.</head>
               <p>R</p>
               <p n="87">87 How may thoſe who are willing to deale in the triall of new inuentions iudge of their goodnes.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18513:50"/>
               <p> A. There are many infallible Rules by which if a diriuatiue Inuention be examined, wee may eaſily iudge of the goodneſſe thereof, but to reduce this doctrine to ſome head, we are to conſider both the generall vertues, and generall faults in inuentions.</p>
               <p>R. 88. What are the generall virtues by which an Inuention is to be examined.</p>
               <p>The vertues of an Inuention are of two degrees, the leſſer and the greater, and each degree is three-fould.</p>
               <p>R. 89. Which are the leſſer virtues of a deriuatiue Inuention.</p>
               <p>A. Theſe three, Equi ſufficiencie, Equi-cheapenes, Equi excellency.</p>
               <p>R. 90. What meane you by Equi-ſufficiencie.</p>
               <p>A. Equall ſufficiencie is when the new Inuention or Emporeuticke is as ſufficient and as good for vſe as the ould.</p>
               <p>So Printed bookes are as ſufficient and as good to reade as written Manuſcripts, and the meale grinded by the winde-milne, is as good and ſufficient to make bread as that which is grinded by the water-milnes, and earthen pipes by the Preſſorian Art, being well made are as ſtrong to hould and conuey water as leaden pipes or potters pots, which two kindes of water conueiances werein vſe long before preſſe-ware pipes were inuented.</p>
               <p>R. 91. What meane you by the ſecond virtue which you cal equi-cheapeneſſe.</p>
               <p>A. The new Emporeuticke is ſaid to haue equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheapenes,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18513:50"/>cheapenes, when as it may be ſould and vttered as cheape as the ould commoditie or inuention which was in vſe before.</p>
               <p>So if Printing bookes be but as cheape to be ſould as manuſcript bookes, then they are ſaid to haue equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheapenes.</p>
               <p>And if Tiles made by the Preſſorian Art may bee afforded to be ſould and vttered as cheape as the tiles made by the ould and ordinary way, then the Preſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware Tiles may well be ſaid to haue Equi cheapenes with ordinary Tiles.</p>
               <p>R. 92. What meane you by the third virtue which you call Equi-excellency.</p>
               <p>A. The new Inuention is ſaid to haue Equi-excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie with the ould, when it hath in it the ſame beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and perfection that the ould commodity of ſale hath, and in the ſame degree, meaſure and equallitie.</p>
               <p>So if Muſcouie glaſſe be as cleare, tranſparent and excellent as greene glaſſe for windowes, then in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the beautie and perfection of the ſubſtance it is ſaid to bee Equi-excellent.</p>
               <p>R. 93. Which are the greater virtues of an inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>A. Theſe three, more ſufficiency, more cheapneſſe, more excellency, all which are eaſie to be vnderſtood, by their lower degrees deſcribed before.</p>
               <p>R. 94. Which are the leſſer faults of an Inuention deriuatiue.</p>
               <p>A. There are three in number, leſſe ſufficiencie, leſſe cheapeneſſe leſſe excellency.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18513:51"/>
               <p> R. 95. Which are the greater faults of an Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>A. There are alſo three, inſufficiency, exceeding dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, exceeding baſeneſſe, vglineſſe or ill fauoured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</p>
               <p>R. 96. What Cannons or rules haue you to iudge of a deriuatiue Inuention, by comparing theſe vertues and ſaults to gether.</p>
               <p>A. There are many, whereof theſe following ſerue to iudge of the vnworthineſſe.</p>
               <p>R. 97. What is the firſt Cannon.</p>
               <p>A. If an Emporeutick haue only in it all the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler vertues, although it may be eſteemed commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a new inuention, then ſurely it will do no good to be ſet vp and followed:</p>
               <p>So if any clay-worke made by Preſſe-ware art, as namely tile, ſlate, free-ſtone, paning ſtone, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings. &amp;c. or greene glaſſe made by Seacoale, If theſe two new inuentions fal out to be but Equi-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, Equi-cheape and Equi-excellent, with old In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of tiles, ſlates, free ſtone, pauing ſtones, archings &amp;c. then ſurely there will be no good to be done by them, becauſe they yeeld no benefit to the common wealth.</p>
               <p>R 98. What is your ſecond Cannon to iudge of the worthleſſneſſe of an Inuention.</p>
               <p>A. If a new Inuention of ſale haue in it but all the ſmaller faults only, it is not to be commended nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will prooue good, for example, if one ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe a Water-worke, to raiſe waters, which is leſſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18513:51"/>ſufficient for that purpoſe, and more chargeable to be erected, and in regard of excellency more imperfect then the ordinary raiſing of waters in vſe, I ſay ſuch an Emporcutick is to bee iudged a worthleſſe Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>R. 99. What is the third directory Cannon.</p>
               <p>A. If a new inuention, compared with the old, be found to haue in it but one of the grander faults, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be accompanied with ſome one or two of the grand, vertues, yet is it to be reiected for ſtarke naught, for there can no good be made of it, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſake ſay that one hath deuiſed to make window<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the pure mettle of Venice-glaſſe, or of the pure ſubſtance of Chriſtall, which is not impoſſible to be done, This his ſale Mechanick will be exceeding deere and coſtly, And therefore although it be more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent or ſtronger, or more ſufficient then the ordinary kind of windowing by greene glaſſe, yet the Inuentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner will neuer do good of it, except it bee to begger himſelfe, and all that ſhall deale in it: for a ſcrap of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquintida, I ſay, marreth a whole meſſe of good pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <p>R. 100. How many directory triplicities is there of this Rule.</p>
               <p>A. There are,
<list>
                     <item>Firſt exceeding deereneſſe, more ſufficiency, more excellency.</item>
                     <item>Secondly inſufficiency, more cheapneſſe, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</item>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:18513:52"/>
                     <item>Thirdly vnſightly baſeneſſe, more ſufficiency, more cheapneſſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>This laſt triplicity although it hath two good grand vertues, yet the buyers of this Emporeutick will not deale with it, becauſe they cannot abide to behold it.</p>
               <p>R. 101. What other triplicities are there of this Cannon.</p>
               <p>A. Three by one grand vertue, and three by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which for breuities ſake I omit.</p>
               <p>R. 102. What other Cannons haue you to iudge of the worthleſſneſſe of an Inuention.</p>
               <p>A. If an Inuention containe all the grander ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and yet tend to the vtter confuſion of Kingdoms and Ciuill Eſtates, then is it by no meanes to bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted or enterprized by any Inuentioner, Of this kind is the <hi>Inuention to walk inuiſible,</hi> if ſuch a deuice may be attained vnto, <hi>to make a barge or ſhip</hi> to flye as well in the ayre as to ſaile vpon the water.</p>
               <p>R. 103. What Cannons or Rules haue you to iudge of the goodneſſe and worth of a deriuatiue Inuention.</p>
               <p>A There are many Cannons likewiſe for this purpoſe, all which are grounded vpon triplicities of the former vertues or leſſer faultes, or intermixt of both.</p>
               <p>R. 104. What is the firſt Cannon.</p>
               <p>A. An Inuention that hath none of the grand faults and hath at the leaſt one of the grand vertues, or more in his triplicity, then is it to be eſteemed good and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable as it apeareth by al theſe ſubſequent triplicities.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18513:52"/>
               <p> R. 105. Recite the triplicitie of this Cannon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A. More ſufficiency, Equi-cheapneſſe, Equi-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p>As for example, earthen tileage is more ſufficient and durable, equi-cheape and equi-excellent then the old way of couering of houſes by woodden pannells, when wood and timber was then as plentifull in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland as is now in Virginia or new found land, and therefore a very good Inuention.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Equi-ſufficiency, more cheapeneſſe, Equi-excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Equi-ſufficiency, Equi-cheapneſſe, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Equi-ſufficiency, more cheapneſſe, leſſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Leſſe-ſufficient, more cheape, Equi-excellent.</p>
               <p>Of this ſort is <hi>Lees</hi> Inuention of loome ſtockings, and the tillage of ground by Plough and harrow, comparing it with <hi>Adams</hi> old tillage with ſpade and Iron rake, which Gardners ſtill vſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. More ſufficiency, Equi-cheapneſſe, leſſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
               <p n="7">7. More Excellency, leſſe-cheapneſſe, Equi-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Equi-ſufficiencyl, eſſe cheapneſſe, more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Leſſe-ſufficiency, Equi-cheapneſſe, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p n="10">10. More ſufficiency, more cheapneſſe, Equi-excellency.</p>
               <p n="11">11. More ſufficiency, more cheapneſſe, leſſ excelency.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:18513:53"/> 12. Equi-ſufficiencie, more cheapneſſe, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Leſſe ſufficiencie, more-cheapneſſe, more-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p n="14">14. More ſufficiency, Equi-cheapnes, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie.</p>
               <p n="15">15. More ſufficiency, leſſe-cheapneſſe, more-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency.</p>
               <p n="16">16. More ſufficiency, more cheapneſſe, more-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency. Which is the beſt and moſt eminent of all other triplicities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 13.</hi> Metallicall Inſtruments defined with their ſeuerall kindes. Lenicks, Preſſe-wares and mouldes deſcribed.</head>
               <p>Reader.</p>
               <p n="106">106. THe Manuſcript Treatiſe or Schedules an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Indenture, as it ſeemeth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth many worthy matters and excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, but it is ſome-what obſcure and obſtruce, both by reaſon that ſome points are implicitely ſet downe, and alſo in reſpect of ſome ſtrange and hard words which I doe not perfectly conceiue or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: I pray you therefore enlarge and deſcribe the ſame Materiall points, in a more familiar phraſe and ſtile, that ſuch plaine men as my ſelfe, who are willing to deale and aduenture in theſe your inuentions, may
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18513:53"/>more fully vnderſtand the purport and goodneſſe of your buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>A. Sir you neede not be offended with the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſticall tearmes, for it hath alwaies beene lawfull to the Authours of new Arts and inuentions at their owne pleaſure to giue names to their new Arts, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and deuiſes which are not ſo vulgarly knowne. Goe but to a Printer, and you ſhall heare many ſtrange words of his inuention and miſterie, as namely <hi>Charrecters,</hi> the <hi>Compoſiter,</hi> the <hi>Long-primer,</hi> the <hi>Pica,</hi> the <hi>Italica,</hi> the <hi>Chaſe,</hi> &amp;c, the like tearmes you ſhall finde in diuerſe other trades in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
               <p>I hope therefore I ſhall not be barred or denyed of that libertie of making choice of words of Arts, for new matters, which is giuen and allowed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery tradeſman in his owne ſcyence and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
               <p>Indeede I confeſſe that ſome points are more cloſely and briefely touched of purpoſe, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was, becauſe I had often promiſed to explaine and illuſtrate them in the printed treatiſe, and it would haue bin both tedious and more chargeable to haue drawne the manuſcript in a prolixe and ample ſort.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe to the intent that no iuſt exceptions may be taken, and that the meaneſt capacitie may perceiue my meaning, I will be ready to explaine and amplifie the ſeuerall contents of my Pattents in as plaine and eaſie mannner as I can thinke or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:18513:54"/>
               <p> R. 107. It is euident by your Pattent, that all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Artes and Inuentions which performe their worke by the helpe and opperation of <hi>Metallicall Inſtruments,</hi> are all of them priuiledged buſineſſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Wherefore I pray you deſcribe at large all the ſorts of <hi>Metallicall Inſtruments</hi> and meanes, which are the ſtrength, nerues, and ſinewes of your priuiledge.</p>
               <p>A. The Inſtruments and meanes <hi>Metallicall,</hi> which are vſed for the producing of Metalique Materialls, or things are (as it was ſhewed before) of two ſorts, <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Peculiar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Common Inſtruments</hi> are ſuch which are bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from other trades, occupations, and myſteries, amongſt which wee haue eſpecially vſe of Smithes, Ioyners, Turners, not onely of their inſtruments and tooles, but alſo of their Emporeuticks which they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily make, as Preſſes, Vices, Screwes, Bellowes, Tongs, &amp;c. made either of Iron and wood, or of both together.</p>
               <p>R. 108. What call you the peculiar <hi>Metallicall Inſtruments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Peculiar Inſtruments</hi> are thoſe that are of the Authors Inuention, being of chiefe and principall vſe for the working of <hi>Metallicall</hi> effects, when they are vſed and conioyned with other <hi>Common Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and they are of two ſorts, <hi>Principall,</hi> and <hi>Leſſe principall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>principall</hi> are thoſe which in the Manuſcript are called by the names of <hi>Lenick, Plegnick,</hi> &amp; <hi>Camminicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18513:54"/>
               <p> R. 129. Define the <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments, which are called by the name of <hi>Lenicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The <hi>Lenicks</hi> are peculiar <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which worke their opperation and effect, by preſſing, impreſſioning or moulding, and that either by thruſting or drawing.</p>
               <p>R. 110. What call you the Emporeutick materials which are made by theſe <hi>Lenick</hi> Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>A. The Materials that are made and brought forth by theſe preſſing &amp; moulding inſtruments, are called Preſſ-wares or mould-wares.</p>
               <p>R. I pray you ſet downe the definition of Preſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares or Mould-wares together, with their ſeuerall ſorts or kindes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſſe-ware</hi> or Mould-ware, is any thing that can bee made, wrought, or formed of clay and earth, not by hand and the round table, as the Potters vſe, nor after the common manner of Tile-making and Brick-making, but by preſſe and mould, or by preſſing and moulding.</p>
               <p>There bee many ſorts or kindes of Preſſ wares by reaſon of different figures, and diuerſe vſes vnto which they are to bee applied, all which kinds are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to theſe two heads: Rude-ware and Polliſht-ware.</p>
               <div type="product">
                  <head>Rude-ware.</head>
                  <p>RVde-ware are ſuch ſorts of Preſſe-ware which after they are preſſed and moulded, require no further ornament.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:18513:55"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Pipeage</hi> is the principall branch of Preſſ-ware, and it is nothing elſe but the making of earthen pipes, for the conducting and ſweeter conueighing of freſh waters, for the ſeruiceable vſe of houſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Field Pondeage,</hi> is a kinde of <hi>Pipeage,</hi> which from higher ſprings and fountaines conueigheth and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributeth water into ſeuerall paſtures, cloſes and fields, and in euery one of the ſaid places, maketh and leaueth a pond of water for cattle and beaſts to drinke in, this kinde is very neceſſary for country townes, where there are but ſome few ſprings, and many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of incloſed paſtures, which in the heate of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer want waters.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Kennellage</hi> is one of the chiefe kinds of <hi>Pipeage</hi> which paſſeth and voydeth away the ſtincking and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy waters of citties and townes vnder earth into the common ditches or ſewers, and this kinde is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the auoiding of noyſome and infectious ayres, eſpecially in the heate of Summer.</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Preſſe-wares</hi> alſo are made <hi>Pumpes,</hi> as ſufficient as thoſe of Lead or Wood, and farre leſſe chargeable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Welleage</hi> is a kind of Preſſ ware for the ſpeedy mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Wells, farre cheaper then the rounds, which are made of Brick to keepe the earth from falling downe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Priuy Funnels</hi> or <hi>Vaults,</hi> may aſo bee made by the Preſſ-ware Art ſo cloſe and ſo ſweete that there can no annoyance or vnfauory ſmels euapoure out or preſſe through them. This kind of Preſſe-ware is very neceſſary for many houſes in the citty, which are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18513:55"/>much annoyed by the leaking and ſincking through the funnels of Brick.</p>
                  <p>As <hi>Walls</hi> are made of ordinary Bricks, ſo may they be made of Preſſ-wares more handſome, cheaper and dureable.</p>
                  <p>Open <hi>Gutters</hi> are made by the Preſſ-ware way, which may ſerue betweene houſes inſtead of Lead, or in Fields to conduct and lead away water, or on the Eues of houſes or Pent-houſes.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Preſs ware</hi> Arte-likewiſe, miniſtrech a kinde of <hi>Tiling</hi> and <hi>Slates</hi> for the couering of houſes more ſubſtantiall and dureable then thoſe that are made by the ordinary way of Tiling, or then thoſe blew and hewen Slates which are digged out of the Slate Quarries.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Spouts</hi> ordinarily are made of Lead, and hanged on the out-ſide of the walls, but Spouteage may more conueniently be made of pipes, brought downe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the middeſt of the Brick walls, for to couueigh raine water into the ſincks vnder the earth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="product">
                  <head>Polliſht-ware.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>POlliſhed-ware,</hi> are ſuch ſorts of Preſſe-wares, which after they are preſſed and moulded, receiue further ornament and beauty, by Turners, Ioyners or engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors tooles, or by Turning, Planing, or engrauing, and there are three degrees of this ornament, for elſe it is meerely by cutting off the edge, when the Preſſe-ware of Clay is liuer dry, or elſe by repreſſing againe,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18513:56"/>which is when they Preſſeware is figured or faſhioned the ſecond or third time with the mould againe. The third degree is by fire, colouring, which is the glar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, glazing or leading of the Preſſe-ware, this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a ſuper-excellent grace and luſtre to the worke, if it be well and curiouſly done and performed, and it hath in it this ſingular prerogatiue. For whereas free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone greeneth preſently with the firſt wet and raine and after in continuance of time becometh ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne with moſſe, or elſe moulteth or crometh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but this ſort of Polliſhed ware continueth alwaies in his natiue and liuely hew, neuer tainting or altering with any weather, no more then the ſtone Iugs or Cruſes, which we vſually drinke out of.</p>
                  <p>Of Preſſewares alſo we may make all kinde of <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingſtones</hi> larger and greater then thoſe which are made by Potters or Tilers, which kinde is very ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. for pauing of houſes, galleries, ouens, courts, and furnaces.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fiſh-ponds</hi> may be both flored in the bottome and waineſcotted on the ſides by the Preſſe-ware Art, ſo ſufficiently, that neither the earth can fall downe, nor the ouſe or mudd to ſwell vp within. So likewiſe for bathes and baynes.</p>
                  <p>Spouts, ordinarily are made of leade, and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the out-ſides of the wals, but they may bee made of turned Pipes being alſo beautified with gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, leading, or other ornaments, ſtamps or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:18513:56"/>
                  <p> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Windowing</hi> and <hi>Menyons</hi> for windowes, which may be made and caſt of white clay, as ſufficiently and ſubſtantially as of hewen bricke or Freeſtone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gardens, Squares,</hi> and <hi>Walkes</hi> are vſually compaſſed and inuironed with railes and pales of wood or ſtone, this may alſo be done by Preſſe-ware, cheapor, ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and handſommer.</p>
                  <p>In a word there is no part or appurtenances in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, which is made either of Bricke, Tile, Lead, Wood, Tarras, or Free-ſtone, which cannot more conueniently be made by the Preſſing Art of caſting, and the reaſon thereof is, becauſe that mouldes may be made to caſt all kinde of Solid ſhapes, figures, and bodies whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>So that from hence alſo we may make Bullets, Globes, Coping ſtones, Archings, Pillars, Columnes, Finiſhings Chimney Fannels, Mantletrees, or Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels for Chimnies, Ceſternes, Coppers to brew in, Waineſcoaring for Chambers, and ſuch other like things, and Vtenſils.</p>
                  <p>R. 112. What are the generall and chiefe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of making of Preſſewares-</p>
                  <p>A. The inſtruments of Preſſing and moulding, which are vſually called by the names of Preſſe and mould.</p>
                  <p>R. 113. How many kinde of Preſſes or Preſſing Inſtruments are there.</p>
                  <p>A. Preſſing or impreſſioning of things is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by diuers meanes, as namely by beating, ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, knocking, or falling.</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:18513:57"/>
                  <p> Secondly, by ſcrewing or viceing. Thirdly by the drawing of flexible girths or cordes. Examples of all which ſorts, are to bee ſeene at my worke-houſe at Highbury, in the pariſh of Iſlington neere London.</p>
                  <p>R. 114. What call you a moulding inſtrument, mould or moulder.</p>
                  <p>A. A <hi>Mould</hi> or <hi>Moulder,</hi> is an artificiall inſtrument which mouldeth, figureth, and proportioneth the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered earth, which beeing forced, paſſeth thorough the mould.</p>
                  <p>R. 115. How many ſorts are there of Moulds or Moulders.</p>
                  <p>A. Moulds are of two ſorts, for either they are as long as the Preſſware, which they make and figure, of which ſort are all thoſe which are called by the names of ſcouring moulds at the <hi>Worke houſe</hi> at <hi>Highbury,</hi> or elſe they are ſhorter then the preſſe-wares which they make, wherevpon they are called <hi>Short Mouldes.</hi> Diuers ſorts both of long mouldes and ſhort moulds, are to be ſeene at the ſaid <hi>Workehouſe,</hi> and therefore I will not further enlarge or deſcribe them heare, but referre the Reader to ſee them at the place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named.</p>
                  <p>R. 116. When a preſſe and a ſhort mould are in one frame vnited together, what is the fitteſt name to call that inſtrument by.</p>
                  <p>A. It may aptly in a word be called a <hi>Preſſe-mould,</hi> which is further deſcribed and handled in the next chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:18513:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAPVT. 14.</hi> The Preſſmould: and the Plegnick Inſtruments defined.</head>
               <p>R.</p>
               <p n="117">117 DEſcribe therefore the Preſſ-mould by his end and vſe.</p>
               <p>A. A Preſſ-mould is a preſſing and moulding In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument for the making of all kind of Preſſ-wares, that is to ſay, all kind of tiles, bricks, pauing-ſtones, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace-ſtones, or any kind of clay-worke or tempered earths whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>R. 118. Deſcribe the Preſſ-mould by his parts and adiuncts.</p>
               <p>A. The Preſſ-mould conſiſteth of theſe generall parts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Two clay-boxes.</item>
                  <item>2. Two Receit tables.</item>
                  <item>3. One Screw.</item>
                  <item>4. Two Preſſours.</item>
                  <item>5. Foure Anti-preſſoures.</item>
                  <item>6. Two Nutboxes.</item>
                  <item>7. Two ſqueaſe tables.</item>
                  <item>8. Two Coane ſpits.</item>
                  <item>9. Two Screw poſts.</item>
                  <item>10. Frames for the ſaid parts.</item>
                  <item>11. Driers and Rammers, which are adiuncts.</item>
               </list>
               <p>There are many ſorts and differences of Preſſ-moulds, euery ſort conſiſting of different parts and adiuncts,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18513:58"/>All which ſhall be at large deſcribed in the ſecond e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Metallica, or in the Appendix, or addition vnto this treatiſe called <hi>Preſſoria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the meanewhile if any be deſirous to ſee both this Preſſe-mould, Engin and the working thereof, at <hi>Highbury,</hi> and at <hi>Iſlinton,</hi> he may haue diuerſe ſorts of them, which in an Artificiall manner doe make all kinde of Clayworkes with extraordinary ſpeed and readinſſe.</p>
               <p>R. 119. I vnderſtand what you meane by Lenicke Inſtruments, I pray ſhew what vſe they haue in Iron buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>A. Firſt, the Lenicke Inſtruments ferue very fitly for the tempering, ſtamping, and comixing of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole, or Stone-cole, that a kinde of ſubſtance being there made of them like vnto paſt or tempered clay, the Preſſe-mould may ſorme and tranfigure that clay-like ſubſtance into hollow <hi>pipe. cole</hi> as it doth earthen pipes.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>pipe-coale</hi> is of very good vſe for the making and working of ſome kinds of Irons and ſteeles.</p>
               <p>Secondly the Lenicke Inſtrument ſerueth very fitly for the breaking and bruſing, ſtamping and beating, tempering and impaſtening of all kinde of Iron oares, whereby they are prepared for the Furnace in a very beneficiall manner and courſe, for when this impaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed oare is by the-engin of the Preſſe-mould <hi>Intubated</hi> and formed into pipes, as if it were Clay or loame, Theſe oare-pipes being made hollow and full of holes are ſooner melted and conſumed by the heate of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18513:58"/>furnace and with farre ſmaller charges of fewell or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring then the ordinary oare which Founders put into their furnace in peeces or gobbits as great as wall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts.</p>
               <p>R. 120. You hauing handled ſufficiently the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Lenickes or Preſſing inſtruments, I pray you proceede end ſhew me what you meane by Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes, which your Maunſcript maketh the ſecond kinde of your <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>A. Plegnicks and <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments which performe their opperation and effect by meanes of their dexterous and artificiall ioynt-mouing.</p>
               <p>R. 121. How many kindes of Plegnicke inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be there.</p>
               <p>A. There are fiue kindes of Plegnicke engins or Machins, the Plegnicke <hi>Bellowes,</hi> the Plegnicke <hi>Milne</hi> the Plegnicke <hi>Schrew,</hi> and the Plegnicke <hi>Rombus,</hi> and the <hi>Reciprocall</hi> Plegnicke.</p>
               <p>R. 122. What odds and prerogatiue differences is there betweene the ordinary bellowes (which Smithes and Mettle-founders daily vſe) and your new deuiſed Plegnicke bellowes.</p>
               <p>A. There are many differences, firſt the Plegnicke bellowes is more handſomely and ſtrongly made, then ordinary refining bellowes, and with farre leſſe expence of leather, for here the leather is not cloſely nailed vpon the wood, but ſtrongly graſted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into the very ſubſtance of the timber, ſo that by this meanes the ioytning of the leather and the wood together, is as thite and cloſe as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18513:59"/>of the boords themſelues.</p>
               <p>Secondly the Plegnick bellowes may be made to blow and ſtreame forth not only could wind and ayre (which is all that ordinary bellowes can doe) but alſo to blow and ſend forth flames of fire, water, vapours and duſt, all which is very neceſſary for the blowing of <hi>Metallicque</hi> ſubſtances, as ſhall be at large ſhewed in the ſecond Edition or in the Appendix called Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica.</p>
               <p>Thirdly the Plegnick bellowes may ſo be made and contriued, to blow ten times more then the ordinary bellowes, and that either by moouing ten times faſter, or elſe by being made ten times greater.</p>
               <p>R. 123. What odds and prerogatiue differences is there betweene the ordinary Milnes and your new deuiſed Plegnick Milnes.</p>
               <p>A. The Plegnick Milnes haue many prerogatiues and conueniences which the ordinary Milning lacketh: and to begin with the Wind milne.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt the ordinary Wind-milne hath nor only his ſailes mounted vp in the wind, but alſo the work-houſe wherin the Milne-ſtones and the Cogg-wheeles grind the corne, by which meanes they are ſubiect to bee blowne downe with ſtormes, but the Plegnick Wind-milne hath his worke-houſe vpon the firme ground, by meanes whereof you may make your Roomes as wide and as large as you will without any hazard or danger of blowing downe.</item>
                  <item>Secondly the croſſe ſailes of the Wind-milne doe mooue <hi>verte callter,</hi> as they cal it, or through the <hi>ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:18513:59"/>or the <hi>nader;</hi> wherevppon ariſeth this inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that the Wind-milne muſt be turned and haled about continually as the wind changeth, but the Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Wind-milne hath his croſſe-ſailes ouer the top of the work-houſe, and they flye round about with a circular motion, paralel to the <hi>Horizon:</hi> whereby it is ready for all windes without turning or haling about.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly this Plegnick deuiſe may be made to go with three or foure paire of Milne-ſtones at once, whereas the wind-milne can go only but with one paire, and by this meanes the Plegnick Wind-milne will grind three or foure times more meale in an houre, eſpecially in a good gale of wind.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly the Wind-milne grindeth only corne, and cannot be made to do any other worke, as the water-milne doth, but the Plegnick engin doth all manner of workes, it will grind corne as well as the Wind-milne, it will ſerue for the Iron furnace to blow the bellowes as well as the ordinary Water-milne, and finally to do any other worke which the Water-milne or Horſe-milne doth.</item>
                  <item>Fiftly the Wind milne ſtandeth ſtill in a calme and when the wind ſerueth not, for there is no meanes to make it goe but by wind, but the Plegnick milne is perpetuall, for when the wind ſerueth not, it is made to go with horſe, and in a ſmall gale of wind the horſe may help to draw and mooue it faſter.</item>
                  <item>Sixtly there are alſo many other conueniences in the Plegnick Water-milne ouer and aboue the ordinary water milne as more at large ſhall bee ſhewed in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18513:60"/>ſecond edition of this treatiſe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>R. 124. How many ſorts of Plegnick milnes are there in regard of the force that mooueth the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</p>
               <p>There are fiue ſorts of Plegnick milnes, The firſt is called the Horſwin becauſe it mooueth both with horſe and wind, the ſecond kind is called the <hi>Horſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> becauſe it goeth both by horſe and water, The third kind is called the <hi>windwater,</hi> becauſe the Wind and the water mooueth the engin ioyntly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>The fourth kind is called the <hi>Horſwinwater</hi> becauſe it is mooued with horſe, wind and water alltogether, and at one time. The fiſt kind is called the <hi>water Pleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> which mooueth either inuiſibly and ſecretly vnder the water and by the water with one rong wheele or elce with two Horizontall wheeles aboue the water.</p>
               <p>R. 125. Did you euer make any of theſe Plegnick milnes to experiment their goodneſſe by triall.</p>
               <p>A. I haue made diuers milne engins to go both by wind and water, in the moddle, but not in the grand Mechanick, and I haue at this preſent a horſwin now framing at Highbury, which the next terme God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall ſtand vppon ſome Turret in London neere vnto the Thames ſide, where all paſſengers by water may ſee it goe and mooue continually. I haue alſo at Pickle herring ouer againſt the Tower a water. leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick which mooueth only by the water, and goeth very ſwift with two paire of Milne-ſtones, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18513:60"/>is deſirous to ſee it may haue it there at a ſhip-Carpenters yard vppon the Wharfe. And thus much of the Plegnick milne.</p>
               <p>R. 126. Define the Plegnick Screw, the Plegnick Rhombus, and the reciprocall Plegnick, which are the three laſt kinds of your Plegnick Engins.</p>
               <p>A. The plegnick ſcrew is an engin whoſe ſpirall line mooueth with one motion, two vice nutts or Matrixes at the ſame time, which no other ſcrew did before, This plegnick ſcrew is very auaileable in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallicall</hi> workes, aboue any other ordinary ſcrew, which hath beene vſually in the common wealth, but eſpecially it is very conuenient for tempering, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and impaſtening of all kind of oares and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coales</p>
               <p>The plegnick Rhombus is an Engin of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and admirable power and faculty, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of quick and ſpeedy motion there was neuer any Machin yet deuiſed, which commeth neere vnto it.</p>
               <p>The Reciprocall Plegnick is an Engin that hath wheeles running reciprocally, turning back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and forewards by one great wheele that mooueth but one way at the ſame time which kind of reciprocal motion was neuer done or performed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by any other Engin.</p>
               <p>This reciprocall is of great vſe for the battering and beating of Iron, lattin, plate, copper, or any other mettles.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:18513:61"/>
               <p> If any be deſirous to be further certified concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth of the admirable motions, opperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and workes of theſe three engins, let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to <hi>Highbury,</hi> and it ſhall be enidently ſhewed and demonſtrated vnto them, in diuers reall moddles and examples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. 15.</hi> Caminicke inſtruments, as fewels, liquours and furnaces defined.</head>
               <p n="127">127. Hauing deſcribed the Lenicke and Plegnicke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, I pray you proceed to the third kinde of <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, which you call by the name of <hi>Caminicks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. <hi>Caminicks</hi> are peculiar <hi>Metallicall</hi> inſtruments, which performe their opperation and effect by their new kinde of furnacing and hearthing.</p>
               <p>R. 128. How many kindes of <hi>Caminicke</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be there which ſerue for the making of all kinde of Irons and other mettles and materials.</p>
               <p>A. There are three kindes, the fewell, the liquor, and the furnace.</p>
               <p>R. 129. Define fewell.</p>
               <p>A. Fewell is any ſubſtance combuſtible being apt or fit to burne, or to make, or take fier.</p>
               <p>R. 130. Rehearſe the ſeuerall kindes and ſorts of fewell.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:18513:61"/>
               <p> A. There are three ſorts of Fewell, whereof fire is made: Wood-fewell, which is either Char-coale or vnburnt Wood-fewell. Secondly Pit-coale or Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coale, and thirdly Bruſh-fewel.</p>
               <p>Char-cole is the Principall and beſt for vſe, but by reaſon of ſcarſity it is growne very deare in our country.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Earth-coale</hi> is that kinde of fewell of ſiring, which is digged out of the bowels of the earth, or elſe vpon the ſuperficies of the earth, of which ſort alſo there are many kindes, hauing difference in their burning. The <hi>Scottiſh coale</hi> is the beſt flamer, and conſumeth away into white aſhes, as hauing in it more vnctiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then ſulpharouſneſſe. The <hi>New-Caſtle coale,</hi> vſually called Sea-coale, is more laſting and dureable then the Scottiſh, for beeing ſtirred vp, it will make a ſecondary or third fire, whereas the Scottiſh-coale conſumeth at once; For which cauſe all Brewers and artificers of London rather vſe this ſort. Howbeit it is not ſo fit for ſome Metalique purpoſes as Scottiſh-coale, by reaſon of the more aboundant heauy ſulphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſubſtance remaining in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turffe</hi> and <hi>Peate</hi> maketh a third kinde of earth-coale, and if they haue any ſulpharouſneſſe in them, it is not ſo heauy and fretting as that which is in the Sea-coale and Stone-coale, the Low-countries vſe for the moſt part this kinde of fewell, inſteed of wood &amp; ſea-coale.</p>
               <p>Bruſh-fewell is the third kind of firing, which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the inward ſubſtance of the earth, nor of the vpper ſuperficies as Sea-coale and Turffe is, but grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon the earth in a bruſhie or twiggie manner, of this ſort is all kinde of ſtubble, Baueings, Straw, Furs, Fearne, Ling, Heath, with other ſtalkes, of hearbes,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18513:62"/>weeds, and vnder-ſhrubs, all which burne with great flames, yet are they of no great heate or long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. Vnder Bruſh-fewell, wee comprehend alſo an other ſort, which is not ſo much vſed for firing, as for lights, as namely, oyles, tallowes, waxes, which are vſed in lampes and candles. Secondly, pitch, roſſen, turpentine, tarre, maſtick, with ſuch like liquids and gums, as iſſue and proceed from trees beeing combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible. This kind of fewell is moſt fit for the <hi>Ventignoll</hi> Mechanick, which hath good and profitable vſe for many purpoſes, where other fewell is not ſo fit.</p>
               <p>R. 131. What meanes are to be vſed to make earth-coale as ſeruiceable for Metalique purpoſes, as wood or Char-coale.</p>
               <p>A. There are three ſorts, the firſt is to bring earth-coale to that equallity of heat, that wood or charcoale hath, that is to ſay, that it maketh neither hotter nor coulder fire then wood or Charcoale doth: the ſecond meanes, is ſo to order and prepare pit-coale, that all nociue proprieties, which are averſſe from all Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſubſtances, may be abſtracted from it, or at leaſt deſtroyed in it. The third meanes is the Addition and infuſion of thoſe deficient proprieties, which as they are in char-cole, ſo ought they to be found in pit-cole.</p>
               <p>R. 132. What meane you by <hi>Caminicke-liquores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. By <hi>Caminicke-liquores</hi> I vnderſtand diuers kinds of intermixt and compounded waters for the lauing, waſhing and ſteeping of all kinde of mettle-Ewres to cauſe them the better to yeeld and giue downe their liquid mettle from their ſlaggs and cinders.</p>
               <p>So that as the Gould-ſmith hath his waters which will ſegar gould from ſiluer, and the Allom-maker his vrines for the ſegaring and bringing downe of his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomes,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18513:62"/>ſo theſe <hi>Caminicke-liquoures</hi> are very behoofe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and effectfull for the ſteeping and tempering of oares, which being thereby prepared, they will the more eaſily let downe their pure mettle being ſeuered and abſtracted from the recrement and droſſe of the cinder and the ſlagg.</p>
               <p>R. 133. Define a furnace.</p>
               <p>A. A ſurnace is a Caminicke inſtrument made and built of furnace-earth; or a furnace is the Artificiall receptacle of fier and fewell, for boyling, nealing, and backing of all kinde of Rawe-materials or Rawe-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>R. 134. How many kindes of Rawe-matters are there for furnaces to worke vpon.</p>
               <p>A. There are fiue ſorts of Rawe-matters, the met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-matter, the liquour-matter, the fiery earth-matter, the dry matter and compounded-matter.</p>
               <p>R. 135. Deſcribe more plainely theſe ſeuerall kinds of Rawe-matters.</p>
               <p>A. The Mettle-matter is that Mettellar ſubſtance which is put into the Furnace to be baked, boyled or nealed, which in one word may be called the Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellar.</p>
               <p>R. 136. How many kindes of <hi>Mettellars</hi> are there</p>
               <p>A. There are three ſorts of <hi>Mettellars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is the raw or baked oare, as it is digged out of the earth, which being put into the furnace melteth downe into two ſubſtances, the one is called the <hi>Glaſs-ſlag,</hi> and th'other the <hi>Sowe-liquour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Glaſſe-ſlage</hi> is a liquid materiall of a glaſſie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance being tough, thicke, and ropy, like bird-lime, it ſwimmeth vpon the ſuperficies of the ſowe liquour, as barme doth vpon beare, or creame vpon milke.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:18513:63"/>
               <p> The ſecond kinde of Mettellar is the ſowe of Iron which when the hearth or furnace hath receiued it, it melteth downe into two ſubſtances, whereof one is called <hi>Ferrica ſubſtantiae,</hi> or the Iron ſubſtance, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is called the cinder or after-ſlagg.</p>
               <p>The after-ſlagg is a liquid materiall which inhereth in the <hi>Ferrica-ſubſtantiae,</hi> as whey doth in a poſſet, or crudds.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ferrica-ſubſtantiae</hi> is tougher then the liquour of the alter-ſlagg, which when it is battred vnder the ſtroke and preſſe of the hammer, the after-ſlagg is ſqueaſed and preſſed out, and ſo the <hi>ſubstance</hi> is made and becometh good Iron, euen as the whey is wrung out by the violence of the Preſſe, and ſo the cruds are made into a cheeſe.</p>
               <p>The third kinde of Mettellar is the could Iron, which when the fordge, furnace or hearth receiueth it, it is nealed and heated into glowing Iron, which glowing Iron afterward is forged by the Smith into diuers Emporeutickes for many-fould vſes and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, as namely into kniues, horſe-ſhooes, Iron-wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, windowe barres, window caſe-ments, and into a thouſand ſuch like Emporeuticks, whereby Smiths get their liuing and maintenance.</p>
               <p>R. 137. In the definition of your Furnace, you make mention of Furnace-earths, I pray you what meane you by them.</p>
               <p>A. Furnace-earth, is any earthy ſubſtance, beeing made and prepared of ſtone, clay, or lome, that ſo it may become the fit and ſufficient matter for the <hi>Cami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> Furnace.</p>
               <p>R. 138. How many kindes of Furnace-earths are there where, withall you build vp your Furnaces.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:18513:63"/>
               <p> There are three ſorts of Furnace-earths. The firſt is the clay-pipes made of white clay, being tempered, wrought, and impaſtned with the duſts and pouders of diuers other things. The ſecond kinde of Furnace-earth, is the clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my morter, which is of the ſame ſubſtance and temper that the Clay pipes are. The third kinde of Furnace earth, is the Furnace-ſtone, which is made into diuers figures, formes and proportions by the Preſſ-mould Art, and of the ſame matter that the other two kinds were made of before.</p>
               <p>R. 139. Define the ſecond kind of Rawe-matters, which you call the Liquour-matter.</p>
               <p>A. The liquor matter is any kind of liquor or liqueable, whether it be cold or hot, which is put into the Furnace Pot, Kettle, Caldron or Copper, to be further heated, and boyled, as namely, all kinds of fatts, tallows, oyles, and all kinds of waters, whether ſimple or compound, as freſh-water, Sea-water, Allomſ-water, Coppreſſe-water, and a thouſand ſuch kindes of liquours.</p>
               <p>R. 140. Define the third kinde of Rawe-matters which you call fiery-earths.</p>
               <p>A. Fiery-earth is any kind of earth or earthy ſubſtance beſides the Mettler which before was deſcribed, as namely all kind of Rawe Preſſe-wares and burnt-earths, before they are burned, baked or nealed, neuertheleſſe the Rawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oare if it be but nealed or baked belongeth to this kinde.</p>
               <p>R. 141. Define the fourth kinde of Rawe-matters which you call dry-matters.</p>
               <p>A. Dry-matter is any kinde of Rawe-matter beſides the three former which were deſcribed before, vnder this head wee comprehend all kinde of paſtes for bread, malts, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frons, papers, wet cloathes &amp;c.</p>
               <p>R. 142. Define the fift kinde of Rawe-matter which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18513:64"/>you call compounded matter.</p>
               <p>A. Compounded matter is any two or more of the former kindes, comming and iſſuing from one furnace and from one fire, together, and at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>R. 143. Hauing thus handled and deſcribed the ſeuerall ſorts of Rawe-matters, which are the things that the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack of the Furnace worketh vpon, labouring to digeſt boile, and concoct them, I pray you now proceed to the diſtributions of the Frunace.</p>
               <p>A. The Furnace in reſpect of the ſeuerall kinds of Raw-matters which it boileth and baketh, is likewiſe of fiue ſorts and kinds, namely the Mettelar-furnace, the liquor-furnace the fier-earth-furnace; the dry-matter-furnace, and the compounded-furnace.</p>
               <p>R. 144. Define theſe fiue ſeuerall ſorts.</p>
               <p>A. The Mettallar-furnace heateth, melteth &amp; nealeth all kind of Mettallers, and ſo worketh them into their Empo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reutick Materials, vnder this head is comprehended all kind of Iron Furnaces or hearths, for any other kind of mettles.</p>
               <p>The deſcriptions of the other foure kindes of furnaces may eaſily be gathered by this, and therefore I referre the further explication of them vntill ſome other time.</p>
               <p>R. 145. What odds and perogatiue differences are there between the ordinary furnaces which refiners and mettle-founders daily vſe, &amp; your new deuiſed <hi>Caminick</hi> furnaces. A. There are many differences both in regard of the forme &amp; figure of making of them, as alſo in reſpect of other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences and prerogatiues, whereof theſe are principall.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Firſt our <hi>Caminick</hi> Furnace is made and built vp of ſuch dureable Furnace-matter, and continually maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſuch fier-reſiſting meanes, that it cannot poſſibly melt or burne down by any <hi>reuerberating</hi> flames or heates whatſoeuer.</item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, our Caminick Furnace is alwayes built
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18513:64"/>with ſome moueable part, as namely the dores, <hi>Fewel-beare, matter-beare</hi> and the <hi>Aſh-beare,</hi> or any other part as wee pleaſe.</item>
                  <item>3. Thirdly our <hi>Caminick</hi> Furnace is built vp with glaſſe windowes for euery ſeuerall roome, ſo that thereby the Furnar may continually ſee and behold both his Rawe-matters and his Emporeutick Materials, and how his fire and Furnace worketh vpon them, which is a ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience which our ordinary Furnaces want.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe forenamed differences and conueniences, with many others, ſhall be truly ſhewed and demonſtrated in the ſeuerall examples of our <hi>Caminick</hi> Furnaces, which very ſhortly (God willing) ſhall be raiſed and built vp at Highbury and at Iſlington.</p>
               <p>R. 146. What &amp; how many are the generall parts of your furnace, which are to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in euery kind of your <hi>Camin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Theſe fiue, the dores, the windows, the fewell-beare, the Matter-beare, and the Aſh beare.</p>
               <p n="1">1.2. The <hi>Dores</hi> are to ſhut and open, and ſo are alſo ſome of the <hi>Windowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Matter-beare</hi> is a generall part of the Furnace, which bereth &amp; holdeth the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the Raw-matters.</p>
               <p n="4">4.5. The <hi>Fewell-beare,</hi> is a generall part of a Furnace which beareth and holdeth the fewel and fire, and the <hi>Aſh-beare</hi> beareth the Aſhes.</p>
               <p>R. 147. What and how many are the roomes of your Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace which are to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in euery kind of your <hi>Caminicks</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. There are foure ſeuerall roomes, which are to bee found in euery Furnace, the Aſh-roome, the Fewell-roome, the Matter-roome, and the Vent-holes.</p>
               <p>The aſhroome receiueth and holdeth the aſhes, the fewell roome, the fewell and firing. The matter-roome receiueth and holdeth the raw-matter. The lower-vent holes receiue and take in the aire, and the vpper vent-holes lets out the ſmoake</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:18513:65"/>
               <p> R. 148. Hauing thus deſcribed your three principall <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments called by the names of Lenicks, Plegnicks, and Caminicks, I pray you deſcribe your other <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments which you called before the <hi>Leſſ-principall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. There are indeed diuers other <hi>Metallicall</hi> Inſtruments which are propper and peculiar of the Authors Inuention, all which ſhall be ſhewed and deſcribed vnto you in the ſecond Edition.</p>
               <p>R. 149. To what end and purpoſe do you publiſh the treatiſe of <hi>Metallica</hi> in print, which deſcribeth and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth all the cheefe Inſtruments of your Inuentions.</p>
               <p>A. There are diuers reaſons which mooued the Author to deſcribe publiquely to the view of the world theſe his <hi>Metallicall</hi> Arts and Inuentions.</p>
               <p>Frſt that it might appeare that his inuentions are new, and of his owne deuiſing, and not ſtolne from any other.</p>
               <p>Secondly it is fit and reaſonable that that which was granted in the Pattent by generall wordes and in an impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit manner ſhould be ſo ſpecially expreſt and defined, that the endeauors and Inuentions of other men being different from his, might not be preuented by him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly that none heereafter ſhould preſume to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or trouble his Maieſty concerning any kind or kindes which are deſcribed and comprehended in his printed trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of <hi>Metallica,</hi> which are all priueledged buſineſſes vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p>And laſtly becauſe the Author by Indenture from the Kings moſt excellent Maieſty is tied and enioyned to print and publiſh his booke of his new Metallicall Inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before the laſt day of Eaſter Terme, whereas he is not tyed to any time for the triall of his Inuentions.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18513:65"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
